<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gainsayer convinced: or, An answer to a certain scandalous paper, subscribed and sent by certain seduced and seditious people to a minister in the countrey: in which the calling of the ministry of the Church of England, the nature of a visible church, the power of the magistrate under the gospel, the right of tithes, with many other points now in controversie, are briefly, fully and plainly cleared, to the satisfaction of those that are wavering; also much of the spirit and many of the errours of the Anabaptists of these daies (who call themselves saints) discovered and confuted. / By T.T. Preacher of the word at Kemble in Wiltshire.</title>
            <author>Thache, Thomas, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E568_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206240</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865414</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117654</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95679)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117654)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 87:E568[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gainsayer convinced: or, An answer to a certain scandalous paper, subscribed and sent by certain seduced and seditious people to a minister in the countrey: in which the calling of the ministry of the Church of England, the nature of a visible church, the power of the magistrate under the gospel, the right of tithes, with many other points now in controversie, are briefly, fully and plainly cleared, to the satisfaction of those that are wavering; also much of the spirit and many of the errours of the Anabaptists of these daies (who call themselves saints) discovered and confuted. / By T.T. Preacher of the word at Kemble in Wiltshire.</title>
                  <author>Thache, Thomas, b. 1616 or 17.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 1, 1-75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Underhill at the Bible in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 75: Tho: Thache.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug. 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117654:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE GAINSAYER CONVINCED:</p>
            <p>OR, An Anſwer to a certain ſcandalous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſubſcribed and ſent by certain ſeduced and ſeditious People to a Miniſter in the Countrey:</p>
            <p>IN WHICH The Calling of the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Nature of a viſible Church, the Power of the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel, the right of Tithes, with many other Points now in controverſie, are briefly, fully and plainly cleared, to the ſatisfaction of thoſe that are wavering; alſo much of the ſpirit and many of the Errours of the Anabaptiſts of theſe daies (who call themſelves Saints) diſcovered and confuted.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. T.</hi> Preacher of the Word at <hi>Kemble</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 JOHN 2. 26.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you concerning thoſe that ſeduce you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 COR 14. 37, 38.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any man think himſelf to be a Prophet, or spirituall, let him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the things that I write unto you, are the commandments of the Lord. But if any be ignorant, let him be ignorant.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 TIM. 6. 3, 4, 5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to wholſome words, even the words of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and to the doctrine which is according to godlineſſe;</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>He is proud knowing nothing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t doting about queſtions, and ſtrifes of words, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cometh envy, ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, railings, evil ſurmiſings,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt mindes, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gain in godlineſſe: From ſuch withdraw thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderhill</hi> at the Bible in Woodſtreet. 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117654:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117654:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>CIRENCESTER,</hi> Grace, Mercy, Peace and Love be multiplied, through the knowledge of God and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are the laſt and perillous times which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 1 2, 3.</note> men do abound in all clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked corruptions, having a form and ſhew of godlineſſe, but denying the truth and power of it: many give Chriſt but <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe, ſaying, Hall Goſpel, but doe betray it. There is a <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis,</hi> two gul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that are almoſt full to the brim of the bloud of ſouls: On one hand ignorance, impiety, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe, drunkenneſſe, chambering and wantonneſſe, ſtrife and envy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe open vices (like a floud) carry down to hell multitudes of ſouls: on the other hand there is a more ſubtle device of <hi>Satan,</hi> whereby many thouſands are deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hereſies, errours, blaſphemies, ſchiſms, under the colour of truth and more then ordinary devotion, eat like a gangreen and canker, and run like a plague from city to city, town to town, family to family, perſon to perſon, to the overſpreading of the <note place="margin">2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whole land, and that without any remedy. Now the loſſe of ſo many thouſand ſouls, which prophaneſſe and errours do daily deſtroy, will cry for judgement to heaven againſt thoſe who uſe not all their endeavours to ſtop theſe miſchiefs, and to apply what remedy lies in them to theſe heavy evils: Thoſe in the ſtate that regard it not, may in due time finde the civill inconvenience of the toleration of, or conniving at theſe things: But the Lord forbid that any of the Lords Watchmen ſhould be Gallios in this, to care for none of theſe things, that the loſſe of ſouls and the flouriſhing of <hi>Satans</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould not touch their hearts. For my own part I muſt ſeriouſly confeſſe, I am ſo conſcious to my ſelf of my many wants and infirmities, that I was very willing to content myſelf to approve my doctrine to God, and the conſciences of my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar people committed to me (for whom I daily be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of the Lord that he would preſerve them, as (bleſt be his holy Name) he hath done hitherto from the infection of theſe times:) But being invited by your pious, painfull, worthy and faithfull Miniſter, and by many of you to beſtow my pains ſometimes amongſt you on your lecture day, I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. And being very ſenſible and apprehenſive of your perill, by reaſon of ſome that
<pb facs="tcp:117654:3"/> are crept in amongſt you, and have already drawn away ſome of your town from your Miniſter, and indeed (as appears in their following paper which you may hereafter reade) from Miniſtry and publike Ordinances, I could not but doe what did lie in the fathom of my power, to prevent the imminent danger of your ſouls, by endeavouring to diſcover ſome of their deceits. I endeavoured (with what clearneſſe I was able) to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon to every ſoul, and to hold forth to you from the Lamps of the Word, ſome r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies of divine light for your direction in theſe dark and miſty daies, wherein 'tis as hard for many poor ſouls to finde out duty as to vanquiſh difficulty. You were my witneſſes (with God) that I delivered rothing but the words of truth and ſoberneſſe: but 'tis hard for whoſome doctrines and ſeaſonable reproofs to finde an open and obedient eat in theſe daies, wherein there are ſo many itching ears abroad, for you may reade in the following paper ſent to me, how many have charged me, which rayling, faction, ſedition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and yet I am confident moſt of them never heard me in thoſe Sermons:) But had the paper charged or aſper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed me only, I ſhould have endeavoured with patience and ſilence, to have put up any thing, but finding the truth ſo charged as you ſhall finde it in their paper by them, I thought it might be my ſinne to be ſilent, and to ſit down and not contend for that. Therefore I was willing to ſet pen to paper, and to take a little pains to vindicate and clear both the truth and my ſelf, from thoſe falſe aſperſions and ſcandals caſt upon it and me: I was reſolved to have ſent them in my anſwer in writing only privately, and the Lord knows how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing I was to appear in publick: but being overperſwaded by many godly judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous friends and brethren (who had the peruſall both of their paper and my anſwer) that the publiſhing of it might conduce much to the clearing of the truth to many poor ſons, who are in theſe daies miſerably puſled by ſeducers in the things herein objected againſt us and anſwered, to the glory of God, and the good of the Church of Chriſt, in directing and informing ſome, convincing others, and pulling others out of the ſnares of <hi>Satan,</hi> in which they lay captive, being (I ſay) upon theſe ground<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned by them, I could not deny the printing of it; And if it may (by Gods bleſſing) have any of theſe eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts upon any (though ſome may ſcoff and ſcorn) yet I ſhall not repent the publiſhing. Now becauſe the occaſion of this work was given amongſt you becauſe the gainſayers herein anſwered, do live among you, and are your neighbours, with whom you have daily converſe, and hereby your ſouls are in much danger of being <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> infected with the ſame errours with which they are carried away ſo he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dlong. In compaſſion to your ſouls, I deſire to dedicate this my anſwer and labour to you, for the preſerving of you from further infection, and enabling you to reſiſt thoſe tempters you may meet with among you. Your loving acceptance of my former pains and labours in preaching amongſt you, aſſures me that this alſo will with the ſame love be accepted and received by you, as 'tis in love preſented to you from me. I ſhall ſpeak no more to you at preſent, but the reſt I ſhall ſpeak to God for you, that he would ſanctifie all means both preaching and printing, for the converting of thoſe that are unconverted amongſt you, for the preſerving thoſe that are yet ſound, for the recalling and reſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe that are gone aſtray, and are ſeduced to live in errour, and for the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that good work which is begun in any of you, that the God of all grace would make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen and ſettle you, and preſerve you by his own <note place="margin">Pet. 5. 10.</note> power, through faith unto ſalvation: If your ſouls reap any benefit by any of my poor endeavours, let the Lord alone receive all the glory and praiſe: all that I ſhall deſire of you is that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſo earneſtly deſired of the <hi>Romans,</hi> I beſeech you, Brethren, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 30.</note> for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt his ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that ye ſtrive together
<pb facs="tcp:117654:3"/> with me in your praiers to God for me. And let me be known to you, as one whoſe deſires, praiers and endeavouss have been, are, and (by Gods grace) ſhall be, to the the utmoſt in my ſphaear, for the making up of the diviſions that are amongſt you, and the building up of your ſouls in your moſt holy faith, Ever reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Churches and your ſervant, (though the weakeſt and unworthieſt of all) in the work of the Goſpel, <hi>Th. Th.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing divine Providence hath made it my lot, and a calling hath induced me (who am leſſe then the leaſt of all the ſervants of Chriſt) to appear among others in the cloud of publike witneſſes to the truth of Ieſus Chriſt, I deſire for thy better ſatisfaction to give thee a word or two of the occaſion of theſe ſheets coming abroad. Whoſoever thou art, thou canſt not but know that we live in times wherein diverſities of opinions are blown (with all license) by the ſpirit of errour over all the land, to the great diſhonour of God, and the indangering of mens ſalvation: And that there are many <hi>Simons</hi> abroad, who (though they are but ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers) doyet give out of themſelves, that they are ſome great ones, and many people give heed to them as to the great power of God: though indeed (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of his Galatians) they are but bewitcht by them, that they ſhould not obey the truth. By theſe men the way of truth is evill ſpoken of, the Miniſters of Chriſt brought into contempt and deſpight, the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God ſlieghted and caſt off all the truths of the Goſpet miſerably invaded by them, and the ſons of thouſands poiſoned and perverted. This is certainly an hour of darkneſſe wherein all ſorts of devils are crept out of their dens, and walk familiarly amongſt us; and <hi>(hinc lachrimae)</hi> O that we could weep tears of bloud, and ſigh to the breaking of our loins for this: that we could ſmite with the hand; and ſtamp with the foot, and cry out, Alas for this! that there are no Orders nor Acts made no new Laws made, nor old Laws execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining, puniſhing, preventing of the ſpreading of the moſt curſed hereſies, errours and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies that ever bell hatcht, or heaven or ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h heard of, But that under a curſed pretence of conſcience and liberty, our poor Church and Kingdome ſhould be a quiet habitation for all the devils in bell. Surely theſe are dales wherein the ſaith of Gods people needs all props that either praier or preaching pulott or preſſe, publike or private inſtructions or admonitions can afford them. And nothing is more neceſſary in theſe times then a ſpirit of diſcerning, whereby we may be enabled to know chaff from wheat, gold from droſſe, a ſerpent from a Saint, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ichriſt from Chriſt. And ſurely it errours were ſet out In their true, clear and live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſhape, that they might be ſeen as they are in themſelves, without any di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guiſe, their bare and unmasked face would be very ugly and abominable to judicious and intelligent mindes.</p>
            <p>Now in the enſuing pages thou ſhall finde, Firſt, <hi>Satan</hi> appearing as an Angel of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, whilſt he is in a great <hi>ſhew of zeal,</hi> ralling againſt the truth, And in the anſwer, thou hoſt
<pb facs="tcp:117654:4"/> his mask ſo far taken off, that thou maiſt plainly perceive him to be the Prince of darkneſſe. The Occaſion both of that Paper and my anſwer was this: Being cald to preach in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture at <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eſter</hi> (where (with grief of ſoul I think of it and speak it) <hi>Satan</hi> hath been ſuffered exceedingly to prevail of late with many, to the ſucking in of moſt grievous errours; The Paper which thou wilt ſee here ſubſcribed by no leſſe then ten, being a ſad Teſtimony of this) I being directed by Providence to preach upon the latter part of the 2<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               </hi> verſe of the 2<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">d</hi>
               </hi> chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> viz <hi>Thou haſt tried them which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſt found them lyars.</hi> The proſecution of the ſeverall doctrines raiſed from the words, ſome ſeemed to be offended at, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I had preached untruths, perſecuted the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I hearing of this offence taken (though none given) when God brought me to preach among them again: in my next turn I preacht upon the ſame text again, and publikely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the Congregation, that if I had or ſhould deliver any thing, in which they were not fully ſatisfied, that they would either ſpeak there, or come to me ere I went out of the town, and I ſhou'd in all love and willingneſſe endeavour to ſatisfie them: not one of them ever come to me, but continued ſtill to revile and ſlander me, and thoſe truths that had been deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. I being enformed of this by their worthy Miniſter <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gregory,</hi> could do no leſſe but write to one of them, who ſeem'd to be ſomewhat offended, and made often complaints to their Miniſter about it, which Letter I had here in the firſt place given you, but that I had no copy of it, and I know not how to gain it out of their hands again. But I appeal to God and to their own conſcien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, whether it was not written in expreſſions of ſoberneſſe, love and meekneſſe, and whether there were any paſſage in that which might juſtly give any offence to any of Gods people: I deſired him to whom I wrote in that Letter, to ſet down under his hand (ſeeing be refuſed to come in perſon to me) what or wherein the offence was which they had taken, or what it was that ſo much troubled them; And I there engaged my ſelf to endeavour a ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>faction, and a clearing of all their doubts to the utmoſt of my power in a loving and brotherly way.</p>
            <p>This <hi>M. Rudge</hi> (for to him I wrote) communicated this Letter to ſome others of that faction, who (as it ſeems) betook themſelves to one <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> a man who was formerly a Stationer in <hi>London,</hi> after that (as I an enformed) a Troopar under the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and having run through ſome other imployments, found this at laſt to be the moſt likely to live by in theſe diſtracted times, <hi>viz.</hi> to turn Preacher: A man (who as you may perceive by the Paper (if it were of his penning) as is moſt probable; it being his hand-writing (as ſome know that have ſeen it) and he being their Teacher) looks upon the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as Antichriſtian, upon our Church as in Church, denies all our pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ike Ordinances, and goes about now from place to place to draw diſciples after him. And by the way take notice, that <hi>That Vigil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Committee of Gloceſter</hi> have approved of, and pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed this man a Paſtor to a Congregation at <hi>Chatleton</hi> in <hi>Gloceſterſhire</hi> near <hi>Cheltnam</hi> where he now exerciſeth his guifts. To this man I ſay (as I am informed) theſe gainſayers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves for aſſiſtance, he being at that time and to this day their Teacher in private. He draws up the following invective, and though it be in many things moſt helliſh, yet ten of them ſet their hands to it, and ſend it to me, wherein they deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y anſwer under my hand. Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly having read it, I found it ſo full of malice and bitterneſse, that I was once reſolved to ſit down and to conceal it, and only in private to pity, to mourn, and to pray for them, that the world might not ſee their madneſſe and ſolly. But ſome of them began preſently to crack and to cry out A Victory, (ſuppoſing their paper unanſwerable) They reported about the Countrey, that they had proved us to be Miniſters of Antichriſt, and that we cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not or durſt not anſwer them, and juſtifie our calling; Being enformed of this by ſome Gentlemen of Countrey, I took my ſelf bound in conſcience to ſend them an anſwer, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had
<pb facs="tcp:117654:4"/> (at laſt) been in private, only to their own hands, had not they themſelves firſt proclaimed it publikely, and had not I been overperſwaded and importan'd by ſome of my Brethren to publiſh it for the ſatisfaction of all that are at preſent in doubt of thoſe things here cleared and the keeping faſt and confirming of thoſe who yet ſtand, and may be in danger of falling into the ſame ſnares: and that which made me ſomewhat more willing to publiſh this, was, the teſtimony which ſome of thoſe Brethren of the Miniſtry, which had the peruſall of it, gave to it under their hands, which thou ſhalt hereafter finde. So that I may ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> writing to his Galatians, <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Paul</hi> an Apoſtle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all the Brethren with me to the Churches of <hi>Galatia.</hi> In writing to them he doth not come forth ſingly by himſelf alone, but as it were guarded with the company and conſent of all his beleeving and faithfull Brethren: <hi>Quaſi dicat Paulus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi> upon the place) At if <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould have ſaid, leaſt I ſhould be alone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adde over and beſides my ſelf all the Brethren which write this Epiſtle as well as I, and hear witneſſe with me, that my doctrine is true, They are all of the ſame minde, they think, write and teach that ſelf ſame things that I do.</p>
            <p>So I can ſay, I and the Brethren with me, who th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nk, write and teach the ſame things, contend for the ſame truth which I doe, which was once delivered to the Saints.</p>
            <p>In their Paper thou ſhalt finde that they ſtrike at our Church, Miniſtry, Magiſtracy, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, all which the Anabaptiſts of theſe times ſtrike at.</p>
            <p>In my Anſwer, I deſire to give thee notice that there are ſome paſſages concerning the maintenance of Miniſters, and the rigbt of tiths, which thou maiſt finde more largely ſet down in that excellent tract of that worthy and learned <hi>D Reynolds</hi> upon the <hi>110<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Pſalm,</hi> out of which I have gathered ſome flowers, the Note in the Margent will direct th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to the Page.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friend,</hi> The Lord knows that with very ſad thoughts I look upon the diſaffection, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and diviſions, which are betwixt Chriſtians in theſe daies, as that which portends more evill, then all our enemies can bring upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, and that which ſadly expoſes not only our perſons, eſtates, poſterities, but that which is deareſt of all, our Religion to the bloudy advantages of our enemies. And the Lord knows that the deſire of my ſoul in this work, is not to make wider or encreaſe, but rather to compoſe our diviſions, rather to beat then to heighten them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing that it may ſome way conduce to the making o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us all of one minde and of one judgement, when we ſhall ſee where the truth is, which I have endeavoured here to clear up. Reade therefore and ſearch the Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, whether theſe things are ſo or no, despiſe not the werkendeavours of thy brother, that deſires only in this Gods glory and thy good, but prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good, abſtain from all appearance of evill: And I pray God that the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who is the light of the world, the morning ſtar, the way, the truth, and the life, would clear up all our darkneſſe, and ſhew all his people the way and the truth, guide them in it, and bring them at laſt to life and light eternall. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> T. T.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We have read this enſuing Anſwer, and finde it ſo full to every particular in the Charge, clearing ſo many materiall points now in contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſie, that we judge the publiſhing of it may be very beneficiall to the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <signed>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ALEXANDER GREGORY Miniſter of</hi> Cirenceſter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WILLIAM EDWARDS Miniſter of</hi> Tethury.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>RICHARD BRITTAN Miniſter of</hi> Biſley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>WILLIAM HALL Miniſter of</hi> Avening.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>RICHARD HALL Miniſter of</hi> Beverſton.</item>
               </list>
            </signed>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117654:5"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your deſire we have preſented you the particulars of thoſe things which we could not but much diſlike, except we ſhould be like many now in our daies, meer time-ſervers and men pleaſers, and ſo prove perſidious to our principles and profeſſions, and make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of faith and a good conſcience, and betray our freedomes into the hands of our bloud-thirſty adverſaries that hath long ſought our downfall.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, We cannot but diſlike with your praying and prating againſt thoſe which formerly you have both praied and preached up (which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſents you meer wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocks) they deſiring nothing but truth and juſtice may take place, and our (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt loſt) freedomes may be repaired, which hath been earneſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y endeavoured by a corrupt Magiſtracy and Miniſtry to deprive us of, for the recovery whereof, our ever to be admired <hi>lebovah</hi> hath raiſed up a poor deſpiſed (yet gallant godly) Army, Who hath faithfully ventured their lives, and God hath crowned their labours with good ſucceſſe, for which good ſervice, you and the whole Kingdome are bound to pray for (not againſt) them, and we truſt while we have life, we ſhall own them and ſtand by them, with heart, hand and tongue againſt all their inverterate and imbittered ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, ſo long as they ſtand for truth and juſtice, as now they doe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We diſlike the misapplication? (as indeed is your common practice, whereby youleade people in dark paths) of that expreſſion <hi>[the baſe are riſen up againſt the honourable]</hi> who do you mean by baſe? and who by honourable? this Riddle wants an Interpreter, theſe are but bals of wilde-fire to ſet the Kingdome freſh on fire, and to fill the hearts of the ſons of Belial with diſhonourable thoughts of the Kingdoms Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in the Army. But if truth may take place with our time-ſerving generation, who are baſe, but ſuch who are content to be baſely cheated out of all their priviledges, ſpirituall and temporall, by a few fine empty notions, who baſely betray the lives and liberties of themſelves and poſterities for preſent ſhadows? who are baſe, but ſuch as baſely falſifie and betray the truſt repoſed in them, but ſuch as ſeek their own advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by a Kingdomes ruine? And who honourable, but ſuch that venture their lives rather then they and theirs ſhould be vaſſels to the baſe wils of any, though never ſo great? Is not that honourable ſervice to bring Delinquents to puniſhment, ſuch Vipers that would eat out the heart of our liberties, which is as dear as our lives (which the Army only doth) Doth not the Scripture declare, that <hi>Righteouſneſſe exalts a Nation,</hi> but what ſhall we ſay to this gainſaying generation, or generation of gainſaiers? who will not underſtand, may it not be truly ſaid to them, as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Nicodemus, Art thou a Ruler in Iſrael, and knoweſt not theſe things?</hi> or rather as Chriſt ſaid to (ſeeing) blinde Phariſees that ſin open-eyed, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9. laſt. <hi>If you were blinde, you ſhould have no ſinne, but now you ſay, we ſee, therefore your ſinne remaineth:</hi> and this we fear is your condition, becauſe we cannot but remember carriage and zeal for thoſe who you now condemn. Oh! what pains was ſpent in their behalf, what praiers was put up for them, what</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117654:5"/>
            <head>The ANSWER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO in charity I call you, (becauſe you ſubſcribe your ſelves ſo) though your Paper, from the beginning to the end, be full of gall and bitterneſſe; and ſavours as much as may be of that enmitie, which God from the beginning, did put 'twixt the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the ſeed of the Serpent.</p>
            <p>Having received your Letter, and peruſed it, I took it (and as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did with the reproachfull letter of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 19.) I did ſpread it before the Lord, who knoweth the ſecrets of all hearts, and judgeth righteouſly.</p>
            <p>And for Anſwer to it, which you deſired ſpeedily, in that I have been thus long about it, I muſt ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did to his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 18. <hi>I would have come unto you (even I Paul) once and again: but Satan hindred me.</hi> So I ſay to you in this caſe, I would have anſwered you once and again ere this, but Satan hindred me. You deſire me to anſwer you in Scripture language, I promiſe you here in the beginning, that I will indeavour in <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 2 laſt ver.</note> meeknes and love to anſwer, and to inſtruct you (with much patience) if God peradventure will give you repentance to the acknowledging of the truth, and that you may recover your ſelves out of the ſnare of the devil.</p>
            <p>But me thinks 'tis ſtrange, that you who deſire Scripture language from others, you who pretend ſo much to the Spirit, ſhould yet ſo farre forget Scripture language, and ſo far put off the meekneſſe of the Spirit, in this your Letter as you do: for I appeal to the world, or rather to God (who knows the hearts from whence theſe expreſſions come) whether it be not fill'd up with that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith grieves the Spirit, <hi>viz: Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe, wrath, anger, clamour, evill ſpeaking, malice: Epheſ.</hi> 4. 31. whether it ſavour not of many of the works of the fleſh reckoned up, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. 20, 21. <hi>viz. hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, envie,</hi> with that revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling which the Apoſtle reproves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11.</p>
            <p>Look upon ſome of your expreſſions: you call us, Time-ſervers, Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocks, blinde Phariſees, Miniſters of Antichriſt, falſe Apoſtles, blood-thirſty men, Popiſh, ſwearers, forſwearers, drunkards, lyars, ſeducers, Jews, Hereticks, men of no Religion, that our Doctrines are deſtructive, and damnable; yea Devils, and the like: and this you have ſet your hands to.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117654:6"/>
            <p> But I ſhall indeavour with the Apoſtle being reviled, to bleſſe; or as the Apoſtle commands us to imitate Chriſt, <hi>who being reviled, reviled not again; but committed himſelf to God, who judgeth righteouſly:</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 23.</p>
            <p>I would willingly ſpeak ſomething to every materiall paſſage in your Letter; but I ſhall paſſe by many of thoſe extravagancies which I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, charitably to beleeve, did unadviſedly drop from your pen, and not take notice of them: for ſhould I ſtay upon every piece of your madneſſe and folly, the profit (redounding to you or me) of ſuch a work, would not countervail the labour.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore paſſe over all your bitterneſſe, baſe ſlanders, your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, your reviling and railing accuſations, with the words of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> the Archangel contending with the Devill, <hi>The Lord rebuke you:</hi> and the Lord help you to ſee from what ſpirit they come, I heartily pitie you (as knowing the Author of theſe) and that nothing of what you have ſent, comes immediately from your ſelves, though by reaſon of your ignorance) you have been eaſily ſeduced, and led to ſet your hands to: and (in that) to ſpeak evil of thoſe things you know not. I ſhall therefore ſpeak onely to ſuch paſſages in your Letter, as do demonſtrate to any common eye, the undeniable footſteps of the ſpirit of Error walking amongſt you: I hope the Lord will inable me ſo to diſcover it to you, that you may at preſent be aſhamed, and grieve that you have been nurſing fathers to any of Satans brood; and that for the time to come, ye may with all carefulneſſe learn to avoid the deepdeceit of that ſeeming An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of light.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To begin.</head>
               <p>You firſt ſay, you preſent me with ſuch particulars, as you could not but diſlike, except you ſhould be (as many now adayes) meer Time-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and men-pleaſers, and ſo prove perfidious to your principles, and prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſions, and make ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray your freedoms into the hands of your blood-thirſtie adverſaries, that have ſo long ſought your downfall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To this I anſwer.</head>
               <p>Firſt, that many of your diſlikes preſented in your Paper are ſuch, that if you father the ground of them upon me, you are falſe accuſers, if you look into the 8. <hi>Joh.</hi> 44. ver. Chriſt will tell you, that the Devill is a lyar, and the father of lyes. And therefore look to it: if I am not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the one half of you at leaſt, (who have ſubſcribed this Paper, and theſe exceptions againſt my praying and preaching) were not preſent, when either of thoſe Sermons were preached; yet it ſeems, (that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117654:6"/> by an implicite faith) you have ſet your hands to them: 'twas bravely and boldly ventured.</p>
               <p>2ly, I anſwer: that (if ever any did in any thing) you have in this your Paper, if you will look upon it, and the times together) declared your ſelves to be meer time-ſervers, and men-pleaſers; and you have herein proved your ſelves perfidious to your principles and profeſſions, and have made ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience: And were it not that the power of the Church, and the golden reins of diſcipline, were at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent violently taken out of her hands, you might (with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander)</hi> be delivered over unto Satan, that you might learn not to blaſpheme.</p>
               <p>3ly, Whereas you ſay, that if you ſhould not have preſented theſe your diſlikes, you ſhould betray your Freedoms into the hands of your blood-thirſtie adverſaries.</p>
               <p>1. I anſwer. Firſt, I deſire you to remember the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2 <hi>Ch:</hi> 19. who ſpeaking of falſe prophets, ſaith, that <hi>while they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption.</hi> It is one bait, which ſeducers do fiſh withall (and never more then in theſe times) <hi>viz:</hi> Promiſes of Liberty and Freedome; and from hence 'cis that they have many followers; becauſe a carnall heart loves liberty, and accounts the commands of God and his Word a yoke, ſtrong cords, and bands: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. But ſuch a freedome and liberty, while 'tis injoyed, brings a man into the greateſt and baſeſt bondage and ſlaverie in the world, <hi>viz:</hi> under ſin and Satan. Now I onely adviſe you, that while you ſo eagerly purſue your Freedomes, and are ſo incouraged with the promiſes, and hope of liberty, that you do not become in it the ſervants of corruption; 'tis an eaſie matter to be deceived herein; <hi>The heart of man is deceitfull above all things: Jer.</hi> 17. 9. and carnall libertie hath a falſe ſhadow of that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian libertie whereunto we are called.</p>
               <p>2ly, For your blood-thirſtie adverſaries who (you ſay) ſeek after your downfall, who they are I know not: I thank the Lord I can waſh my hands in innocency, from thirſting after your blood; the Lord knows I hate none of your perſons; and I can ſpeak that for your ſouls, which <hi>Paul</hi> did to his <hi>Romanes,</hi> 10. Chap. 1. ver. <hi>Brethren, my hearts deſire and prayer to God for you is, that ye may be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To come to your diſlikes.</head>
               <p>Firſt, (you ſay) you cannot but diſlike my praying and prating againſt thoſe, whom I have formerly prayed and preacht up, <hi>viz:</hi> the gallant godly Army; and this preſents us meer weather-cocks, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117654:7"/>
               <p> I anſwer: Firſt, to your diſlike of our praying for, and againſt<hi>—while our gallant godly Army,</hi> kept in Gods wayes, and in their own ſphear, they were honorable and precious in the eyes of all Gods ſervants, they then had our hearts, our help, and our prayers for ſucceſſe therein; and we have bleſt our ever to be admired <hi>Jehovah,</hi> for crowning their labour and valour with ſucceſſe: But if theſe or any other for whom we have prayed, and whom we have preached up, do decline that pitch, and we then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, I hope no underſtanding indifferent man can for this call us Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocks; they that do, are revilers, and ſlanderers; I leave it to the Lord (who beſt can) to judge betwixt us and them, who have turn'd about, and who have kept their ſtation.</p>
               <p>2ly, As for my praying againſt them, the Lord (who is a God hearing prayer) knows that my prayers have been ſuch for them, as for mine own Soul; <hi>viz.</hi> that God would ſhew them all the evill of their wayes, (I hope you will not make them infallible) that he would give them repentance unto life; that ſo their iniquity might be blotted out: Now I am much miſtaken, if the underſtanding and wiſe in heart, do call this praying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a man: I ſhal thank any Man that hath any intereſt at the Throne of Grace, that will thus pray againſt me; if this, I ſay, be to pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one.</p>
               <p>In the next place, where you call our preaching, prating; if you be not quite brazen and impudent (me thinks) yee might bluſh and be aſhamed of your uncivill and unbeſeeming language, to call the preaching of that (which I challenge you or all the world to prove) to be any thing but the truth of God;<hi>—Prating.—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is no new thing; <hi>Paul,</hi> tels us that the preaching of the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> is to them that periſh fooliſhneſſe. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 18. And <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, by I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous <hi>Athenians</hi> (though preaching Chriſt) yet counted a Babler. <hi>What will this Babler ſay? Acts</hi> 17. 18. ver. Here was language as perverſe as their Religion, and for my part, I expect no more mercy at the Tongues of men, then the Apoſtles had; In all Ages the wicked bend their Bows, and ſhoot their Arrows, even bitter words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper. In the ſecond place, you ſay you diſlike the miſapplication of that place of Scripture,</hi> Iſa. 3. <hi>the baſe are riſen againſt the honourable, you ſay it is my common practiſe whereby I lead men in dark paths; you ſay this is a Riddle that wants an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter; and theſe are but Bals of wild-fire, to ſet the Kingdom freſh on fire, and fill the hearts of the Sons of</hi> Belial, <hi>with diſhonourable thoughts of the Kingdoms wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies in the Army. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. Firſt, That that place of Scripture is no Riddle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117654:7"/> (if you know what a Riddle is) and ſo needs no Interpreter at preſent, if you doe not ſhut your eyes, ſuch plaine places cannot be hidden to you, and as for the miſapplication of it, which you charge me withall, you charge me falſly, for I made no Application of it all to any; you venture to expound the words in your Paper, &amp; to ſhew who are the vile and baſe, and who the honorable, <hi>viz.</hi> who baſe (ſay you) but thoſe who baſely falſifie and betray their truſt repoſed in them? who baſe, but ſuch as ſeek their own advancement by a Kingdoms ruine? Truly theſe are baſe ones indeed: The Lord help you to apply, as rightly as you have expounded, and then I doubt not but you will ſee who they are that are led in thoſe dark paths which you ſpeak of.</p>
               <p>2ly, In that you ſay 'tis my common practice, to miſapply Scripture, and to lead people in dark paths: I ſay here as <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3, 4, 5. being diſgraced by ſome Corinthian Doctors, and falſe teachers that were crept in amongſt them (whoſe ſteps many do follow in theſe dayes, and do make it their work to beget a prejudice in people againſt their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) with me, it is a very ſmall thing, that I ſhould be judged by you, or by mans judgement; for I judge not my own ſelf; for I know nothing by my ſelf (in this which you here lay to my charge) yet am I not hereby juſtified, but he that judgeth me is the Lord: therefore judge nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time, untill the Lord come; who both will bring to light the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of darkneſſe, and will make manifeſt the counſels of all hearts.</p>
               <p>3ly, In that you dare ſay, that any parts of Scripture, are Bals of wilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire, &amp;c. Remember what St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith of an evill tongue, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3. 6, &amp;c. <hi>The tongue is a fire, a world of iniquity, and is ſet on fire of hell:</hi> the tongue that dares caſt iniquity upon God, or his Word, is ſurely ſet on fire of hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pap.</hi> 4ly, In that you charge us as ſeeing-blind Phariſees, and ſay that 'tis our condition, to ſin with our eyes open, becauſe you cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our carriage and zeal for thoſe whom we now condemne: Oh what pains (ſay you) was ſpent in their behalf? what prayers put up for them? &amp;c. is all this buried in the grave of oblivion? and what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? have theſe Worthies (ſay you) fallen from their faithfulnes? No, no.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. In this caſe you nor I muſt not judge, at leaſt ſay whether they have or no: onely all that we deſire is, that the Lord may judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and them. I ſhall ſay no more of this, in this place, becauſe I have ſpoken ſomething to it already, in my Anſwer to your firſt diſlike of our praying for, and againſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paper. </seg>
                  </label> I ſhall ſpeak but one word more to your ſecond head, and that is this: you ſpeak of the honorable ſervice of ſome in bringing Delinquents to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117654:8"/> juſtice and puniſhment, and that from this, that the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That Righteouſneſſe exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts a Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> For anſwer, let me onely tell you here, that that juſtice which exalts a Nation, muſt be, both for the matter and merit, as alſo for the manner and form of doing it, unqueſtionable and clear; and muſt not be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without an orderly Authority derived either immediately from God, <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Gaud.</hi> Rel Prot.</note> or mediately from thoſe Politick Laws and ſettled Magiſtracies, which are Gods ordinances amongſt men. But where the execution of Juſtice is unjuſtly uſurped, and carried on without any warrant from Gods Word, or mans Laws, either as precept and rule, or example; ſuch an execution of juſtice, is a turning of judgement into wormwood, and doth depreſſe and bring a Nation lowe under the judgements of God, rather then exalt it: I ſpeak not this in reference to any perſons, or actions; onely to inform your judgement a little.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place, you charge me with praying that the Lord would bring the King out of the hands of thoſe that had reſtrained him, and what was this (ſay you) but a ſtroaking Malignants on the breaſt? and a making the Army odious in the eyes of the ſimple deluded ones?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. Firſt, that this accuſation is from the father of lyes too, if ten more of you had ſubſcribed it. This you take upon truſt too, from thoſe who it ſeems have already given ſo much libertie to their conſciences, as to make no conſcience of a lye: having forgotten it ſeems, or counting thoſe places <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> where the Spirit of God tels us, that a lying tongue is one of thoſe ſeven things which is an abomination to the Lord, and which he hates: <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 17. And (if this be an old Teſtament text) that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4. 25. <hi>Putting away lying, ſpeak every man truth to his neighbour:</hi> and if you had as much truth and honeſty as you ſeem to lay claim to (no diſparagement to your honeſty) I could bring twenty and ten as honeſt men as your ſelves to teſtifie the contrary. What I ſaid, I truſt I am able to make good, as being nothing but what was, and yet is, juſtifiable before God and men, and that was this: I prayed, that God would deliver the King out of the hands of thoſe that ſought his deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and this was no more then what I was bound in conſcience to do (while he was living) being one of his Subjects, and having many Oaths, Proteſtations and Covenants, ſacred and civill tyes and bonds lying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, obliging and ingaging me to obedience and loyaltie; and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in my place, the preſervation of his perſon, and the promoting of his honour and ſafetie. And certainly you have not lived ſo long, nor undergone ſo many Offices in the Common-wealth (as ſome of you have)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117654:8"/> but ſome of the ſame Oaths and Covenants have been more then once taken by your ſelves: Now I muſt plainly confeſſe to you, that (what new Religion ſoever you have lately met with to abſolve your conſciences from ſo many oaths and obligations, in all which, you have call'd the Almighty and all ſeeing God of heaven to be both a witneſſe to you, and an avenger upon you) I for my part am (as yet) ignorant of any power under heaven that can abſolve me from ſuch oaths taken before God to my lawfull Soveraign. I know but one power that pretends to it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to do it, and that is the Pope. But for God, I doubt not but you (who pretend ſo much to walk by the rule of the Word) do know, what a ſwift witneſſe the Lord is againſt ſuch as ſwear falſly by his name, and what a revenger he is to ſuch ſins. Read <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. 4 firſt verſes, there's a flying roll of curſes, that ſhall enter into the houſe of him that ſwears falſly, it ſhall remain in the midſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it with the timber thereof, and ſtones thereof. Now (I ſay) though you may (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance) have found liberty of conſcience, yet (for my part) I cannot yet find liberty to ſwallow down ſuch a camell as this is without choaking.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pap.</hi> 2ly, Whereas you ſay, that in this we ſtroaked the Malignants, and had this end in it, to make the Army odious, that theſe prayers ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour more of fleſh then ſpirit, more of zeal then knowledge, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from ſelf ends, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. I bleſſe God, I have learnt to bear with patience theſe, and more ſuch reproaches as theſe are; the Lord forgive you: what my prayers were, and from what ſpirit they proceeded, and what I aymed at in them, as my end, the Lord knows; that's my comfort: and you ſhall know too one day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Again, whereas you charge us with not laying down our Call from the Biſhops; I ſhall more fully ſpeak to that hereafter; you give me occaſion in the following part of your Paper to clear that, and therefore I ſhall not meddle with it here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the fourth part you ſay, I prayed that the Lord would take the Sword out of thoſe hands in which now it was, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ten of you have ſubſcribed this too: Pray how many of you dare ſay, that you heard me ſpeak the words? This you take upon hear-ſay too: And let me tell you, that if you give credit long to the informations of thoſe, who have thus learnt to ſtretch their mouthes, you'l forfeit your own credit quickly: I ſay in this to you again, if the number were trebled, I am able to make it good, by as good, and far greater teſtimony, hat this too is falſe, for there was not ſuch a word ſpoken: you tell me
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117654:9"/> in the next branch, that true Miniſters ſhould be no falſe accuſers. May the people be ſuch. The ſame ſpirit tels us, that every righteous man will hatelying: <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. 5. The Lord in mercie give you grace to repent (if that be not too legall a grace to be wiſht to ſuch high flown Chriſtians) but however let me tell you (that except you repent) the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>A falſe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe ſhall not be unpuniſhed: and he that ſpeaketh lyes ſhall not eſcape.</hi> Prov. 19. 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the fifth place, you ſay, you cannot but wonder, at that abominable aſſertion, and falſe aſperſion hinted in our expreſſions, as if the Army would down with truth, with Government, faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſet up falſe Apoſtles, &amp;c. and how falſe this is, the world ſees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. I cannot but wonder at your abominable ignorance, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, to call that a falſe aſſertion and aſperſion, and ſo cruelly to condemne it as abominable, and a falſe accuſation; which yet in the ſame place you ſay was but hinted at in ſome expreſſions; bluſh and be aſhamed (if you be not paſt it.)</p>
               <p>2ly, For what the Army puls down, or intends to ſet up, it is not for you nor me to meddle with now; therefore no more of that: let it ſuffice that the world ſees (as you ſay.)</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paper. </seg>
                  </label> 3ly, That only which I chiefly would anſwer in this fift place, is this:—you ſay, you conceive that none are true Miniſters in our account but ſuch as come by State approbation, and have their call from the Biſhops, and they from the Pope, and ſuch is ours if you miſtake not.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> To theſe things I will anſwer particularly. Firſt, whereas you ſay that (you conceive) that none are true Miniſters in our account but ſuch as come by State approbation.</p>
               <p>1. I anſwer. I ſhall herein give you a certain account of my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and opinion herein, which I hope I ſhall be able to make good againſt you, and all other gainſayers. To proceed plainly, and by degrees.</p>
               <p>Firſt then I ſay, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt as he doth inviſibly teach and govern his Church by his holy Spirit, ſo in gathering, preſerving, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing, building and ſaving thereof, he uſes Miniſters as his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and hath appointed an order of ſome to teach, and others to learn in the Church; and that ſome ſhould be the flock, and others the Paſtors.</p>
               <p>Again, beſides the firſt founders of the Church of Chriſt, extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſent, and furniſhed with the gift of miracles, whereby they might confirm the doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine of the Goſpel, he appointed alſo, ordinary Paſtors and Teachers for the executing of the Miniſtery even untill his coming
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117654:9"/> again unto judgement. See <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 11, 12, 13.</p>
               <p>2ly. I ſay that it is not lawfull for any man, how fit ſoever, and how much ſoever inriched with gifts, to undertake this Office of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, in the Adminiſtration either of the word or Sacraments, by the will of private perſons or others, who have not power and right to call; much leſſe is it lawfull for any, by their owne judgement or arbitrement, to aſſume &amp; arrogate the ſame to themſelves: But before it be lawfull to undergo that ſacred Miniſtry (in Churches conſtituted) a ſpeciall call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (yea beſide a lawfull Election (which alone is not ſufficient) a miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ſending, or (as commonly it is termed) ordination, is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; I ſay, neceſſarily required, not only to avoid confuſion, and to ſhut out Impoſters, but by reaſon of divine inſtitution delivered to us in the holy Scriptures. See theſe places, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 15. <hi>How ſhall they preach except they be ſent.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 10. where the Apoſtle ſhewing, how <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> ſhould be qualified; ſaith, <hi>Let theſe firſt be proved, and then let them uſe the Office.</hi> Againe, 1. Tim. 4. 14. <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> Againe, 1. <hi>Titus</hi> 5. <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in Creet, that thou ſhouldeſt ordaine Elders in every City as I had appointed thee.</hi> Again, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 2. 3. &amp;c. where you find that the Holy Ghoſt commanded the Prophets and Teachers in the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> to ſeparate <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> for the work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he had called them; and the Text ſaith, that <hi>when they had prayed and faſted, and layd their hands on them, they ſent them away:</hi> Can any thing be more cleare? <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were queſtionles gifted men; they had a Call from the Holy Ghoſt, the text ſaith ſo plainly, but yet this was not ſufficient, till the Prophets and Teachers there, had faſted and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and layed their hands on them: Once more ſee the 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> the firſt 4 verſes. <hi>Every High Prieſt, taken from among men, is ordained for men, in things pertaining to God, that he may offer</hi> &amp;c. And in the 4<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> verſe. <hi>And no Man taketh this Honour to himſelfe, but he that is called of God as Aarou was.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now you muſt know that there is a double calling, neceſſary to a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pencer of the myderies of Salvation, <hi>viz.</hi> inward and outward; the inward inableth them, the outward authorizeth them to diſcharge their ſacred Function. Where there are gifts (if God incline the heart of the heart of the Party to enter into the Miniſtry) there is an inward calling, yet this alone (as I have ſhewed) ſufficeth not, without an outward call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either ordinary or extraordinary—extraordinary callings (ſeeing miracles are ceaſed) we are not now to expect; and if any (as many now) do pretend to ſuch, we are not eaſily to believe and give way thereunto,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117654:10"/> to the ordinary calling, by faſting and prayer, and the impoſition of the hands of the <hi>Presbytery—</hi>as before mentioned. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 14. and by the way you may take notice, that though the word <hi>Presbytery</hi> be (in theſe dayes) ſo diſtaſtfull, yet 'tis Scripture proof.</p>
               <p>From hence now my account (which you ſaid before you did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) is this: that all that take upon them, to execute the office of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, ought to have a Calling, not only inward, but outward thereunto; I ſay, not by the Approbation of the State, but the probation and approbation of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> &amp; the impoſition of their hands: And they who preſume to undertake to be your Miniſters without theſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their gifts be (which many Lay-men, Artizans, Mechanicks, and broken Tradſmen in theſe dayes pretend to) they are no Miniſters of the Goſpel, but deceivers and Intruders.</p>
               <p>And thus I have ſhewed you, whom we account Goſpel Miniſters.</p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall indeavour to remove the great block at which you ſtumble ſo often, that Crum which troubles you ſo much even to your choaking almoſt, and that is the Ordination of ſome of our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters by the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You ſay we have our call from the Biſhops, and they from the Pope, and ſuch is our Call, if you miſtake not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Tis well you put in an [if] here, if you miſtake not. Tis no news for you to miſtake, and your miſtakes are very foule ones; ſuch that every underſtanding man cannot but wonder at, that they ſhould come from ſuch men as you, who pretend ſo to light: But it appeares plainly, that the new light which hath lately ſhune about you, tis as that extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light, that did ſhine about <hi>Saul</hi> at his converſion (if I may make ſuch a compariſon) it hath ſtruck you quite blinde at preſent, and the light that is in you, appears to be darknes, <hi>and how great muſt that darknes be;</hi> as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 23. The Lord in mercy to your Souls, haſten the time, wherein the Scales may fall from your eyes, I ſhall indeavour to pluck off ſome of them at preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> We have (you ſay) our call from the Biſhops, and they from the Pope, and this (if you miſtake not) is our call to the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, in that you ſay our Biſhops are from the Pope; do you meane in their Names or Functions? Theſe are both from Scripture, from the Apoſtle, See 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. <hi>If any man deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſires a good work.</hi> Againe, 20. <hi>Acts</hi> 18. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the flock, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops,—</hi>ſo the word is in the originall.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117654:10"/>
               <p> Or 2ly, do you meane that they are Popiſh in their opinion and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? if ſome have been ſo, you cannot condemne them all for that; no your ignorance and your malice, would then ſhame you to all the world; for the contrary hath been witneſſed, by the blood of many famous Martyrs, eminent in the Prelacy, which in freſh Records you ſhall reade hath been ſhed for God, againſt the Harlot of <hi>Rome;</hi> and by the excellent labours of <note place="margin">Bp. <hi>Hall</hi> Apolog: againſt Browniſts</note> others, (and thoſe late Biſhops of this Church) whoſe learned Pens have puld downe more of the Walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> then all the Corner-Creeping <hi>Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> will be able to do while the World ſtands.</p>
               <p>Or 3ly, Do you meane that they are from the Pope in their Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency, ſuperiority and Lordlines, if in any thing, it muſt be in this? Now to this I anſwer; That we received our Ordination from them, as they were Biſhops and Elders of the Church, not as they were Lords; and if they were Lords for their externall dignity, yet they were not Lords of of our faith, and if we looked upon them in any thing of their Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it was as they were our Elders, and Fathers, not our Maſters.</p>
               <p>Farther yet I ſhall deſire you to take notice, that in the making any man a true Miniſter of the Goſpell, there are ſome things required, which are eſſentiall to the Miniſtery, without which a man is not a true Goſpell Miniſter.</p>
               <p>Againe, there are ſome other things which are but circumſtantiall, or Accidentall, which a man may have, or may not have, and yet be a true Goſpell Miniſter.</p>
               <p>Now if I may make it appeare to you, that we have all the Eſſentiall requiſites of Goſpell Miniſters (I hope you may be convinct, that we are Miniſters, and Miniſters of the Goſpell (how opprobriouſly ſoever, you cenſure our calling (or elſe you muſt make the contrary appear to us.</p>
               <p>Now then if God hath made us able to teach, if he hath inclined our hearts to the office of the Miniſtry, and hath made us deſirous to teach: if he hath ſeparated us, for this cauſe to the worke, if our People have had a lawfull Election, if we have been admitted upon due tryall, both of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and People, if we have been ordained by impoſition of the hands of the Elderſhip, and prayer, if (I ſay) we have had all theſe things (which appeares to all the World) and yet be no true Miniſters; pray let me know from you, what is further required, to the ſubſtance of a Goſpell Miniſtry? If we have all this, and yet have our calling from the Pope, let me know I ſay from you, what is a Goſpell calling; and if this be not according to the will of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the Scriptures, (but Popiſh) ſhew me what is.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117654:11"/>
               <p> A little farther yet in this point, if God upon this call hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a charge to us; if he hath followed our Miniſtry with power, and bleſt our labours with gracious ſucceſſe, if (I ſay) God hath done this for us, and by us; with what face dare you challenge our Miniſtry as Popiſh and Antichriſtian? I am ſure you cannot but grant the Miniſtry in generall, to be the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ward means by which God gives grace, and increaſes inward grace. Now then that Miniſtry by which God hath given grace &amp; increaſt it, that miniſtry is of Gods appointment: now whether God hath not given grace and increaſt it by our Miniſtry, ſome of your owne hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences (if ever you had grace, which you will be loath to deny) ſhall be our witneſſes. I am able to make it good to ſome of you (and that by your own confeſſions) that God hath followed our Miniſtery with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and bleſt our labours with gracious ſucceſſe, even in ſome of your hearts, whoſe tongues are now ſo buſie to call in queſtion and to deny the truth of our Calling.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, If Epiſcopall Ordination be a Popiſh and Antichriſtian rite, as you ſay tis, I deſire to learne from you, what was the Chriſtian for me or manner of admitting men into holy places for 1500. yeers after the Apoſtles time, can you ſhew me any other Ordination that was heard of, at leaſt approved of for the ſpace of 1500 yeers? during which time, it there were no lawfull Calling, there were no Paſtors feeding and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the flocks; and if no lawfull Paſtors, then no viſible Churches: Now pray tell me, if they were not a true Church in thoſe ſeverall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies and ages while they lived under Biſhops; where had Chriſt a viſible Church upon earth ſince the Apoſtles times? Certainly if the Calling of their Paſtors and Teachers were not (at leaſt for ſubſtance) ſufficient (though perhaps not perfect) Chriſt never had any in his Church ſince the Apoſtles left the earth.</p>
               <p>And having thus given you an account of ours; I pray, tell me ſeriouſly (ſeeing you have ſeparated from ours as abominable, as you ſpeak after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in your Paper) whence is that office of the Miniſtery which you now follow? I dare ſay, not from Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, nor their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: what Church ever in the world can be produced (unleſſe in caſe of extremitie for one turn) whoſe conſpiring multitudes made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Miniſters at their pleaſure? what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule of Chriſt preſcribes it? what reformed Church ever did or doth practice it? what example warrants it? where or when have the inferiors layed hands on their ſuperiors? what Congregation in Chriſtendome affords you a pattern? The Apoſtle indeed tels us, that <hi>the time ſhould come, when men ſhould not indure ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117654:11"/> 
                  <hi>but after their own luſts ſhould heap to themſelves teachers, having itching ears: And they ſhall turn away their ears from the truth, and ſhall be turned unto fables.</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 3, 4. And if ever thoſe words of the Apoſtles were fulfilled, 'tis in theſe times upon which the Lord hath caſt us. And certainly there was never any fable a more arrand device of man, then ſome part of that Miniſtery of yours ſo much gloried in, for ſincere correſpondence to the Primitive Inſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pap.</hi> In your ſixth place, you ſay, you diſlike not our zeal in Preaching againſt errors, hereſies, and Hereticks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Truly we thank you for nothing; 'tis a wonder almoſt: do you not indeed diſlike it? 'tis well there is ſomething that comes not under the penaltie of your diſlike: hut if you do not diſlike it, I marvell why you (above others) do ſo wince at it; ſurely this argues that there is ſome gawled place. Where iſt?—you tell us ſomething in the next place. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paper. </seg>
                  </label> You ſay we take not a Goſpel-way to convince, and to reprove them; as firſt to prove them ſuch. 2ly, by the ſame rule to reprove them, and then caſt them out, if you are a Church of Chriſt,—which if you are, we wonder at your diſorder, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> We thank you for your inſtructions, and teaching us, how to reprove, and convince hereſies and hereticks. And I deſire to let you know, that we have known, and do know, and have ſufficiently proved, and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome of your errors, and ſhall (if God permit) do more in that way hereafter: but for our caſting them out, in the firſt place you ſave us that labour, for you ſeparate your ſelves; and beſides if you did not, the Church is (at preſent) ſo rob'd of her power, that <hi>Ochim, Zim</hi> and <hi>Jim,</hi> Owles and Satyres, all the devils in hell, are broke looſe amongſt us, and may have a quiet habitation amongſt us; and we are (at preſent) ſtript of all power, (but that of our prayers, and the immediate power of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God) to caſt them out.</p>
               <p>You need not (me thinks) wonder ſo much at our diſorder, ſeeing we live in an age, wherein all order and government in Church is counted Popery, and Antichriſtianity, and perſecution of tender conſciences.—For our diſorders, I ſhall ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Galathians,</hi> I would to God they were even cut off, that trouble our order: but they ſhall in their due time receive their reward, and bear their judgement whoſoever they be. <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 10. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But I cannot but take notice of your ſuppoſition (if we be a Church) which if you are, we wonder at your diſorder.</p>
               <p>It ſeems you conclude us to be no Church, becauſe of ſome diſorders: what? is it come to an [if] with you? truly you have made haſte to run
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117654:12"/> thus far alreadie: what are we no Church? To ſatisfie you in this, let me ask you, do you know what makes and conſtitutes a true viſible Church? It appears you do not, and therefore I will tell you.</p>
               <p>According to the Scriptures, and the joynt conſent of all Proteſtant Churches in the world, the ſincere preaching of the Word, and the due adminiſtration of the Sacraments, conſtitutes or makes a true viſible Church. Again, do you know what is a true particular viſible Church? It is a particular company of men, profeſſing the Chriſtian faith known by the two marks above-mentioned, <hi>viz:</hi> the ſincere preaching of the Word, and the due adminiſtration of the Sacraments.</p>
               <p>Now I tell you (and if you have any thing to ſay in denyall of it, I ſhall make it good to you) that by Gods mercy we have the true uſe of the Word and Sacraments, and all other eſſentiall gifts and graces of God to make us a Church; and though (at preſent) by reaſon of many ſuch diſorderly fellows as your ſelves, and by reaſon of the want of ſome helps in execution of that power and authoritie which Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted our Church withall, there may be many diſorders amongſt us; and we are annoy'd with many practicall evils: but yet ſo long as the Goſpel is it ſelf amongſt us; ſo long as the aire of that is clear, ſo long as we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and inviolably hold the foundation; I tell you, that though every rayler may tearm us no Church, and every <hi>Ignoramus</hi> may doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we be a Church or no, yet there is no Seperatiſt, ſhall be able to prove us no Church: If you can do it, I deſire to hear what you can ſay againſt us: and I promiſe you (if you can prove us no Church, and prove your ſelves to be one) I will be your diſciple: and I will acknowledge that you have received more new and miraculous light then all the <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Featly</hi> Dipper dipt.</note> Ruſſet Rabbies, and Mechanick Enthuſiaſts, that ever I yet heard or read of.</p>
               <p>For ſurely though ſome of the Maſters of your new way have bitterly inveighed againſt the Hierarchy and tyrannie of ſome of our Prelates, yet the ſame tongues and pens have both juſtified our Church, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told it: many have indeed oppoſed ſome of our Appendances and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances (which we diſlike with them) but they have acknowledged and defended our ſubſtance. And many of our late moſt rigorous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have not more diſliked our Epiſcopall Government, then imbraced our Church: we are but little beholding to your charitie, who ſeem to queſtion our true viſibilitie of a Church, and the world cannot but laugh at it; and we cannot but pitie your ignorance, that you, for ſome corruptions and diſorders amongſt us, ſhould hold us to be no Church, and ſo ſeparate from us.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117654:12"/>
               <p> Again, are we no Church? pray then (tell me) what are you? can you be ſo impudent as to deny this, that ſome of you have been begotten again by the word of our Miniſtery? will not your own conſciences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you? lay your hands upon your hearts, what ſaith conſcience to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his? Have you not I ſay (ſome of you) acknowledged, doth not conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence yet acknowledge, that (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 10. according to the grace of God which hath been given to us, ſome of us have layed the foundation of Chriſt in your ſouls? though now another buildeth thereon (as the Apoſtle ſaid) I am ſure of this, <hi>Other foundation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an no man lay, then that is layed, which is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Now let every man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake heed how he buildeth thereon, he that builds upon this foundation, wood, hay, ſtubble, this work will not abide, but ſhall be burnt, and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall ſuffer loſſe, and though himſelf be ſaved, yet it will be ſo as by fire. Again, what ſaith Conſcience to this? have not many of you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that ſince your new birth, you have ſuckt much conſolation and ſtrength from the breaſts of our Church? have not many of you been nouriſht, and grow'd thereby? and are we now doubted to be a Church? what's the matter? is the food changed? is there any alteration in that? or have you a ſick mans pallate, that can relliſh no wholſome ſavourie food? Surely, ſurely, it is not becauſe there is no ſavour in the food, but becauſe of the diſtemper of the pallate. The Lord help you to ſee your condition: there is no diſeaſe more dangerous, then thoſe which rob the party of his ſenſes: and every one will tell you, that tis a ſad ſigne of death, when he that is deſperately ſick will tell you that he is well, and feels nothing. I beſeech you remember from whence you are fallen (in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oofing your firſt love) even out of the Church already, whither will the next fall be: I tremble to think of it, if God give you not grace to repent, and to do your firſt works: therefore let me preſſe upon you St. <hi>Peters</hi> counſell, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Laying aſide all malice, and all guil, and hypocriſies, and envies, and evil ſpeakings; As new born babes, deſire the ſincere milk of the Word, that you may grow thereby: If ſo be that ye have taſted that the Lord is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Once more: If you look upon us as queſtioning whether we be a Church or no, and ſeparate from us as no Church, let me ask you one queſtion more: Have you renounc'd your Baptiſme? if you renounce our Church, you muſt lay down that, or elſe you are ſtill of our Church; for that was the ordinance by which you have been all admitted, and initia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into our Church. Now, I ſay, if that be not renounc'd, you are yet members of our Church, which yet you ſay is no Church; and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117654:13"/> you muſt either be members of a Church, which is no Church; (and if ſo) conſider, and tremble to think of your condition; for whiles you are out of the Church, you are ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid his <hi>Epheſians</hi> were before their Calling, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Without Chriſt, aliens from the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Iſrael, ſtrangers from the covenants of promiſe, having no hope, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in the world.—</hi>Now if it be not thus with you, what new Church are you members of? (I hope you are able (at theſe yeers) to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your faith, and you would have us to look upon you as belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) have ye then been dipt lately? or hath the weather been too cold? I beleeve all the arguments of your new Paſtor have ſcarce (as yet) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with you for this; what ſigne or ſeal have you then, of your being admitted into a new Church? That which makes me doubt of this, and ask the queſtion, is becauſe I ſee you ſtill retain your old names taken in your Baptiſme, in our now forſaken Church; you ſubſcribe your ſelves, <hi>Thomas,</hi> and <hi>William,</hi> and <hi>Giles,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Roger,</hi> &amp;c. do you not look upon theſe names too, as received in that Antichriſtian ordinance, and ſo away with them, as rags of Antichriſt, and ſuch ſuperſtitious things as not to be retained any longer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your next place, under your ſixth branch, you complain how the poore, deſpiſed, forſaken, godly people of the Land, have not worldly powers to ſide with, but againſt them; and perſecution hath been raiſed by thoſe worldly and ſecular powers againſt the godly, to death, and baniſhment, witneſſe the late indeavours and deſires of the Presbyterian Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In this I muſt note two or three things: Firſt, if you mean your ſelves, and ſuch as you are, by the poore godly people of the Land, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you will no more complain (I hope) of being deſpiſed, and forſaken, and perſecuted by worldly powers; you are yet alive, and you need not fear baniſhment, or perſecution to death; for you have now gotten the worldly ſecular powers (as you call them) to be with you, and not againſt you: Now if you make the ſyding of the worldly powers, againſt a people, to be alwayes a mark of the godly people of the Land; what then are you at this time, with whom the preſent powers of this part of the world (in which you live) do ſyde?</p>
               <p>2ly, I cannot but ſmile at, or rather pitie your ignorance here again; you ſay you are perſecuted by the ſecular powers of the world; witneſſe the indeavours of the Presbyterian Miniſters: wherein you ſay plainly, that the indeavours of the Presbyterian Miniſters, are the indeavours of the ſecular powers of the world: how groſſe and abſurd is this igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117654:13"/> learn for ſhame to diſtinguiſh better againſt next time, leſt the world hiſſe at you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> 3ly, You ſay, the ſecular powers raiſe perſecution againſt the godly to death, and baniſhment; witneſſe the indeavours of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here again you plainly ſay, that the Presbyterian Miniſters raiſe perſecution againſt the godly. We may here juſtly ſay (with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid)</hi> we live among men that are ſet on fire, even the ſons of men, <hi>whoſe treth are ſpears and arrows, and their tongue a ſharp ſword. Pſal.</hi> 57. 4. and 59. 7. <hi>Behold, they belch with their mouth, ſwords are in their lips:</hi> But we doubt not but our God will deliver us (as he ſaid) from the reproach of them that would ſwallow us up.</p>
               <p>Again, I cannot conceive what your meaning ſhould be, except it were the late teſtimonies of the Presbyteriall Miniſters to the Solemne League and Covenant, and to the Truths of Jeſus Chriſt, againſt Errors, Hereſies and Blaſphemies: (your meaning can be nothing but this) Now if you call this an indeavour to perſecute the godly of the Land; you muſt neceſſarily conclude, thoſe that hold errors, hereſies, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies to be the godly of the Land. (and if that be your opinion, 'tis moſt abominable to all thoſe that know any thing of God, or of truth) And I tell you farther, that the baniſhing, or putting to death, thoſe who after conviction perſiſt in hereſies and blaſphemies, is no more then the written Word of God allows, and commands (if you be not gotten alreadie above the Word, and ſo lay that by) neither can it be called perſecution no more then the hanging of a thief, robber, or murtherer, by the Laws of the Land, can be ſaid to be perſecution, when the juſt and deſerved puniſhment of their wickedneſſe is inflicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Again you go on in your ſixth exception, and ſay 'tis no new thing for worldly wiſe and ſeeming godly men, to perſecute the Saints and power of godlineſſe; and the very ſame thing is practiſed in our age; and that if men were acquainted with the working of the myſtery of Iniquitie, they would never be ſuch ſlaves to time-ſerving ſelf-ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, who onely ſeeks their gain from their quarters; and thoſe that will not put into their mouthes, they will raiſe war againſt them; and this you poſitively ſay, doth evidently appear in me in my ſlighting and reproaching thoſe whom I formerly rejoyced in, but now are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by me, Sectaries, and troublers of the State, though I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt you but the caſe of <hi>Daniel,</hi> concerning the Law of your God, and will not now beleeve as I beleeve, and put into my mouth to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117654:14"/> feed you with untruths; and therefore I now diſ-own you; and on the contrary, own, imbrace, and hugg in my boſome, thoſe openly wicked, and prophane, which formerly I profeſt my ſelf a ſtranger to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Friends, waſt in cold blood? were you in your right ſences? did you not for that preſent lay by that little reaſon, truth, honeſtie, and charitie that you pretend to, when you did ſet your hands to theſe things? did you not forget that of Chriſt: <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36, 37. that <hi>for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry idle word that men ſhall ſpeak</hi> (much more for every lying, reviling, ſlandering word) <hi>they ſhall give account thereof in the day of judgement. For by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi> Will you juſtifie theſe words before God or men? or will they not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne you without repentance? Here you charge me, with perſecuting the Saints, and the power of godlineſſe, that I am a time ſerving ſelf-ſeeking man, who ſeek onely my gain from other mens quarters: that I raiſe war againſt thoſe that will not put into my mouth; that I ſlight, and reproach, and call thoſe Sectaries, whom I formerly rejoyced in, becauſe you will not beleeve as I beleeve, and put into my mouth to feed you with untruths; and that I now hugg and imbrace, the openly prophane,—&amp;c.</p>
               <p>Are ye able to make theſe accuſations good againſt me? truly you ſpeak very largely, as if your tongue (that unruly evil member full of deadly poyſon, wherewith you pretend to bleſſe God, and yet do curſe men made after the ſimilitude of God) were your own; and that none could or ſhould controul you.—Had I received ſuch words from open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophane men, or from profeſt devils, I could have born them better; but to be ſo traduced, by men that would be accounted underſtanding men, men profeſſing conſcience as their rule, yea from profeſt Saints, truly this makes me much more to ſuſpect, and miſtruſt the truth of that you profeſſe, then ever I did before: remembring the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 3. 12, 13, 14, &amp;c. <hi>Can a fountain ſend forth at the ſame p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace ſweet water and bitter? Can a figtree bear olive berries? or a vine, figs? ſo can no fountain yeeld both ſalt water and freſh. Who is a wiſe man, and indued with knowledge amongſt you? let him ſhew out of a good converſation his works with meekneſſe of wiſdom. But if ye have bitter envying and ſtrife in your hearts, glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y not, and lye not againſt the truth. This wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is earthly, ſenſuall, divelliſh.</hi> See alſo <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 11, 12.</p>
               <p>1. But to anſwer the particulars: Firſt for my perſecuting of the Saints, and the power of godlineſſe; I do here appeal to the Lord Jeſus, who takes all ſuch perſecutions of Saints, as done to himſelf: <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 5.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117654:14"/> In this point (I ſay) I call heaven and earth to witneſſe, and ſhall ſay with <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7. 3. 5. <hi>O Lord my God, if I have done this; if there be this iniquity in my hands: Let the enemy perſecute my ſoul, and take it, yea, let him tread down my life upon the earth.</hi> And as he in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 19. <hi>Thou Lord haſt known my reproach, and my ſhame, mine adverſaries are all before thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2ly, In that you ſay I am a time-ſerver, and ſelf-ſeeker, and that I ſeek onely my gain from other mens quarters, &amp;c. What time-ſerver I am, let the times judge; and for the ſeeking of my ſelf, or my gain from my quarters: I thank the Lord that my rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of my conſcience, that in all quarters (eſpecially to you-wards) I have preached the Goſpel without covetouſneſſe: and the gain that I have ſought for, hath been the gain of ſouls to Jeſus Chriſt, (knowing that this alſo ſhall turn to my gain) In this (I hope) you will allow us to be covetous: and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>ch: Being allowed of God to be put in truſt to preach the Goſpel, even ſo we have ſpoken, not as pleaſing men, but God, who tryeth our hearts. Neither at any time uſed we flattering words, (as ye know) nor a cloak of covetouſneſſe (God is witneſſe) neither of men ſought we glory, nor of you, nor yet of others: when we might have been burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as the Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi> Yea you your ſelves are witneſſes (and God alſo) that I have both travell'd to, and laboured amongſt you in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel of God; neither ever yet have I been chargeable to any one of you (to my beſt knowledge and remembrance) no not for a peny, though moſt falſly and impudently you here charge it upon me; And if I had ſought my ſelf, and my own gain, ſo much as you ſpeak of, ſurely I ſhould have ſought me out ſome more charitable quarters, then I ever yet found yours to be: But the Lord forgive you your unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, returning, and requiting me in this, evil for good.</p>
               <p>3ly, In the next place though you cannot but be convinc'd of this in your own conſciences, that you never as yet put any thing into my mouth, yet pray tell me; when or wherein have I endeavoured to raiſe warre againſt you? will this be made good, or muſt I put it into the number of your moſt unchriſtian-like ſlanders?</p>
               <p>4ly, Whereas you ſay that I ſlight, and reproach, and diſ-own you, whom I formerly rejoyced in; becauſe you will not beleeve as I beleeve, and put into my mouth to feed you with untruths: I anſwer as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Thoſſalonians,</hi> 1 Ep. 2 Ch. latter end, that ye were our joy, and our glory, and the crown of our rejoycing, while ye ſeemed to ſtand faſt in the Lord: But ſince you have been ſo fooliſh (as he ſaid to his <hi>Galathians,</hi> 3. Ch: 1. ver.) to be bewitcht by others not to obey the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117654:15"/> truth; you muſt pardon us this wrong if we be in heavineſſe for you: and though we be far from ſlighting or reproaching any (as you falſly object) yet (I ſay again) you muſt pardon us, if we diſ-own you in your errors; which of us it is that hath changed, let the Lord judge betwixt us, whether our doctrine, or your profeſſion and practice, hath been, yea and nay. We dare appeal to the ſame God, and to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that the word of the Goſpel which hath been preached among you, by us, was not, is not, yea and nay, but in Chriſt was and is yea.</p>
               <p>But farther, you ſay we ſlight and diſ-own you, becauſe you will not beleeve as I beleeve, and put into my mouth to feed you with untruths.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. Firſt for your beleeving as I beleeve; for my belief, I ſhall ſay, firſt as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 7. <hi>If any of you truſt to himſelf that he is Chriſts, let him of himſelf think this again, that as he is Chriſts, even ſo are we Chriſts:</hi> my belief is in the Lord Jeſus, neither have I ever endeavoured to invite or intice you to any other belief then the faith in Jeſus Chriſt. And whoſoever he be that ſhall preach to you any other Goſpel, or another belief, though he were man, or Angel from heaven, I muſt ſay as <hi>Paul, Galat.</hi> 1. 8, 9. <hi>Let him be accurſed.</hi> What other beleef you have lately found out, that you will not beleeve as we beleeve, I know not.</p>
               <p>In the next place, for your putting into my mouth, to feed you with untruths.</p>
               <p>I call you and all the world to witneſſe againſt me, and to make it to appear to me, what untruth I ever fed you withall: even here in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo (I thank my God) I can ſay with the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17. <hi>We are not as many, which corrupt the Word of God; but as of ſincerity, but as of God, in the fight of God, have we ſpoken in Chriſt.</hi> And as he, 4. Chap. 2. <hi>We have renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty, not walking in craftineſſe, nor handling the Word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the truth, commending our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, for your putting into my mouth (which you here again ſpeak of) I here again anſwer you, I need no other witneſſe againſt you then your ſelves: I here ask you again, Where, or when any of you, did put any thing into my mouth, though my mouth hath been open to and for your ſouls in preaching the Goſpel of conſolation to you; Though I have ſown unto you ſpirituall things, yet when or where have I ever reaped any of your temporals? Certainly therefore (if you have not put on a whores forehead) you cannot be aſhamed of this your ſo falſe and groundleſſe a reproach, which you ſo often here caſt upon me.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place, whereas you charge me with imbracing and hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117654:15"/> in my boſome, open prophane ones: I deſire you to let me know, who are thoſe open prophane ones whom I do now ſo imbrace and own: I beleeve l muſt ſet this by amongſt the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next part of your ſixth branch, you ſay, If we were Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, we durſt not give the childrens bread to dogs, much leſſe preſſe others to ſin to partake with ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> I wonder that you do not ſet the ſaddle upon the right horſe (as the Proverb is) either ſhew us plainly who does ſo; or elſe confeſſe to your ſhame, that you let fly at all, at randome, and ſpeak more out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice then knowledge. And ſurely ſuch tongues want bridles: I dare challenge you to make it good againſt any of us, where ever you have known any of us, to give the childrens bread to thoſe whom we have known to be dogs: or where ever we have preſt any to ſin; or to partake with thoſe whom we or they have known to be dogs: ſurely this too, will prove to be another of the ſame, with your former ſlanders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your 7th branch you ſay 'tis your deſire, that wolves may be brought to light, that you may know them and avoid them; but we fear ſome that would be thought true Apoſtles, will prove falſe, and ſo muſt and ought to be avoided, as the moſt deſperate enemies to the truth, and to the profeſſors thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In all this we joyn with you, and (never fear it) I will warrant you, that ſome who now appear to you to be true Apoſtles, and are now transformed into the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Miniſters of <note place="margin">See 2 Cor. 10. 13, 15.</note> righteouſneſſe, and ſpirituall men; when their vizor is pluckt off, will be ſeen in their colours: God hath promiſed it, and God will perform it, that their folly and their madneſſe ſhall be made known unto all men, and they ſhall proceed no farther. See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Here again you ſay, ſome are afraid to come to light, and therefore have gained Orders from Authoritie, that none muſt queſtion what they ſay in publick; and be ſure they will never meet in private: ſo they will avoid all occaſion of being queſtioned. Therefore let all the wiſe in heart judge who are afraid of light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. That we are ſo far from avoiding the light, that we creep not into houſes, we preach not what we deliver in corners and Conventicles, but in publick Congregations And that there hath been any order gained from Authority, that none ſhould queſtion what we ſay in publick, is falſe: who gain'd that Order (that was put out by Authoritie) I know not; but (if I do not miſ-underſtand it) it onely prohibits that diſorder, which (for all your large libertie afterward
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117654:16"/> mentioned in your Paper) you would ſcarce admit of in your private meetings, <hi>viz:</hi> that in the midſt of your exerciſe, you ſhould be diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and call'd out upon, to anſwer every queſtion, which every piece of ignorance in the company or congregation ſhould propoſe: but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe once ended; as our doors (as well as yours) are open to all comers; ſo if any man hath any thing to ſpeak, he may ſpeak without fear of being queſtion'd by the Magiſtrate. And as you ſay you have often heard your Teachers deſire, ſo I ſay (for my own part) I deſired it my ſelf in publick, but the laſt time (ſave one) that I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eached to you (&amp; ſo have others before me there) that if any man hath any thing to ſay againſt what we deliver, they ſhould ſtand forth and freely ſpeak, (onely deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (as you ſay) that they ſhould ſpeak in order, in love, for edification, and one by one) or that you would come to us before we went out of your Town to be reſolved, which none of you did, (though intreated in a Chriſtian-like way to do it) but when we were gone from you, (and as you thought out of the hearing of it) then with moſt black and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt mouthes, and tongues full of lying and bitterneſſe, have gone from place to place, and traduced us and our doctrine; let the Lord judge, and let your own conſciences ſpeak, whether this be not ſo; and if it be truth, we ſay with you, let the wiſe in heart judge who are afraid of light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> For your 8th branch: wherein you ſay you diſlike our Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniſh confuſion in making no difference twixt the Church and the world, but jumbling them together, contrary to the minde of God in Scriptures, and the clear practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In a part of this Anſwer before, I have ſhewed you what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is twixt the Church and the world; in ſhewing you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the minde of God in Scriptures, and the clear minde of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, what doth conſtitute a true viſible Church: and if you would have had a larger Anſwer to this ſilly objection and diſlike, you ſhould have ſhew'd us wherein our jumbling them together doth appear, and I doubt not, but we ſhould have given ſatisfaction, at leaſt a reaſonable anſwer, though perhaps that would not have ſatisfied you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your ninth diſlike is this; That we cry out againſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe perſons as overthrowers of publick Ordinances; and neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the perſons who, nor the manner how.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Did not our Saviour Chriſt tell the diſciples when they were together, that one of them ſhould betray him; yet he did not tell them preſently which, nor the manner how; he did not tell them that 'twas
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117654:16"/> 
                  <hi>Judas</hi> by name: however (when they asked him) he gave them a ſigne by which they ſhould know him, as well as if he had named him, <hi>viz: He to whom I ſhall give a ſop,</hi> &amp;c. So here I ſhall not give you the very names, as to ſay 'tis you <hi>Thomas,</hi> or you <hi>William,</hi> or you <hi>Giles,</hi> or you <hi>Roger,</hi> &amp;c. yet I will give you a ſigne in a word or two, by which you ſhall know the very men.—Thus then: They that ſeparate from, and they that refuſe, and do lay down the practiſe of publick ordinances, and do cry out againſt them. Theſe are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey that do what they can to overthrow publick ordinances: In theſe few words now, ye have the perſons who, and the manner how: I think now I need not give you the perſons by name; by this that I have ſaid, (if the Lord help you to try your ſelves and your brethren by rhis note) you will quickly ſee who are the men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your next place you ſay, That it hath been offered by ſome of you, to Indicate the true uſe of ordinances, according to Primitive Inſtitution, yet you could not prevail with our partie to give a meeting to try it by the light of Gods Word; and now again you offer it to me, that when I ſhall appoint a time you will chearfully give a meeting to clear the truth from all falſe practiſes and innovations of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. That except you were men of more modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and meekneſſe, then your Paper ſhews you to be, except you knew better how to bridle your tongues, and to over-rule your mad paſſions, to which you have ſo freely given the reins in your Paper) I cannot blame any man for refuſing to give you a meeting. Surely it is to be feared, that inſtead of clearing up the truth, ſuch meeting (with ſuch men) might prove to be but juſt ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to avoid and ſhun, <hi>viz:</hi> Vain bablings, which will increaſe to more ungodlineſſe, a ſtriving about words to no profit, but to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the hearers. And again he cals them <hi>fooliſh queſtions, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſtrivings, which are unprofitable and vain.</hi> See 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14, and 16. v. <hi>Titus</hi> 3. 9.</p>
               <p>But thus far I entertain your proffer (becauſe you ſhall not think that we are afraid of you) that if any among you, or any one for you, (for as for your own parts (poore men) I know you are no way able to undertake ſuch a work) but if any of your new inſpired Rabbles, for you, I ſay, ſhall undertake under his hand and yours, to ſet down what that truth of doctrine and practice is which you hold, profeſſe, and practiſe in ordinances; I do here promiſe you that I ſhall be readie to entertain it, and to give you in, either my aſſent to it, or my diſſent
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117654:17"/> from it; as I ſhall finde it upon faithfull tryall by the Word, to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſſonant from, or agreeing to the Primitive Inſtitution of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Or if you can charge us with any falſe practiſes, or Innovations which we allow of, let me hear what they are, and I ſhall give you in my Anſwer. And I take this to be far the better way (ſo you will do it without railing and ſcolding, and as you ſay in Scripture language) to ſatisfie and reſolve both your ſelves and us in the truth; for words ſpoken (you know) are apt to be forgotten, and oft miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly miſtaken; but words written, remain, and you may all take copies of them, and lay them by you) to pawſe upon; and I ſhall give you a fair occaſion of this in my Anſwer to the laſt clauſe of this your ninth branch. Wherein you ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You deſire to be aſhamed and confounded, for your former evill practice, and for all your former abominations, in the abuſe of the precious ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, not onely as you were Atheiſticall, Papiſtical, Prelatical, but alſo Presbyterial in Doctrine and Diſcipline, contrary to Chriſts inſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. If you have any ſhame in you, you never had more cauſe to be aſhamed and confounded in your ſelves; then for ſome things in this your profeſſion: ſome things (I ſay) which are abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and they are theſe which follow.</p>
               <p>Here firſt you plainly confeſſe, that you have been Atheiſticall, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall, Prelaticall, and Presbyteriall already, in your Doctrine and Diſcipline: truly 'tis no marvell to ſee you ſuch whiſtlers, and to ſee you carried about like empty clouds, with every winde of new doctrine that you meet with now adayes; if you have paſt through ſo many changes alreadie: let's view them a little.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you ſay, you have been Atheiſticall in Doctrine and Diſcipline, here's a riddle indeed (as you ſay) needs interpreting: poore men! let me ask you again, did you know what you did when you ſet your hands to this? how miſerably have you been betrayed to diſcover your ignorance, and to lay your ſelves naked thus to the view of all? Pray tell me, what doctrine and diſcipline have Atheiſts? do you ſee your ſimplicitie? Atheiſts are ſuch as live without a God, and do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge none; ſuch are ſaid to be Atheiſts: Now I ſay, what doctrine or diſcipline is there amongſt Atheiſts? I think you would be looked upon as admirably inſpired men; men that have deep revelations; if you would ſet out the Atheiſts religion in doctrine and diſcipline: In theſe times wherein there are ſo many new ones that are ſprung up; I never
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117654:17"/> yet heard of this till now from you.</p>
               <p>Next, you ſay, you have been Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſticall and Prelaticall; this is not ſo much to be admired, becauſe there have been ſome Papiſts and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates that have had their doctrine and diſcipline in <hi>England;</hi> but I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew (before your confeſſion here) that <hi>Thomas Clutterbuck, Giles Hancox, Thomas Sheapheard, Calcb Self,</hi> and thoſe of you whom I know, (for truly I cannot ſay that I know you all, or that I have ever (to my knowledge) ſeen ſome of your faces) I ſay, I never till now knew that you had been Papiſts in doctrine and diſcipline: and I am ſorry to hear it now: and for theſe your abominations, I cannot blame you (nay I ſhall help you what in me lyes) to be aſhamed, and confounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n your ſelves for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> But laſtly you ſay, you deſire to be aſhamed, and confounded for all your abominations, as you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> been Presbyteriall in doctrine and diſcipline contrary to the inſtitution of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer, (and here I ſhall give you that occaſion which I but now promiſed you) firſt what your abominations have been, whileſt you profeſt and lived under Presbyteriall doctrine and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline I know not: 'tis like, very many; be aſhamed and confounded, and repent quickly for them.—But for the Doctrine and diſcipline Presbyteriall in it ſelf, that which the Orthodox Presbyterian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this Kingdom, do now profeſſe, and deſire to practice: I do here undertake to make it good to you, and to him that ſhall undertake it for you; That it is according to the Inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles; this I ſhall do when I hear what you have to ſay againſt it: and if you have any ſhame left in you (which you profeſſe to have) I hope the Lord will then help you to be aſhamed of, and confounded for all the abominable ſlanders you have caſt upon it, and to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and confounded in your ſelves for that you have ſo cauſleſly and ſinfully ſeparated from it, and have fallen from the Ordinances and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt, to the practiſe of thoſe new ones that never had ground or being, other then in the vain and fooliſh ſpeculations of ſome newly inſpired men.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paper. </seg>
                  </label> As for your tenth branch, which is nothing but ſinfull raylings, and revilings; I ſhall not look upon that as worth times and words to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. You call us, men of blinde zeal, you ſay we are deſperate and damnable in opinions and practiſes; That moſt of our own cloth and calling are Malignants, Prelaticall, drunkards, ſwearers, lyars, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, that we are moſt againſt thoſe that are moſt conſcientious; and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117654:18"/> greateſt friends to prophaneneſſe, and prophane ones, &amp;c. a roll of <hi>Shemei</hi>'s and <hi>Rabſhekah's</hi> language: the Lord help you to ſee your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in it, and to repent, that your iniquity may be pardoned, and forgiven by the Lord, for my part I forgive you freely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall onely ask you, how you would take it to have your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument turned upon you? Thus: Some new Lights, Separatiſts, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents are raylers, revilers, ſlanderers, ſwearers, drunkards, lyars, follow all abominations; if one ſhould ſay, ſuch are ſome of you, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you are all ſuch, and to be condemned for ſuch; how would you like the concluſion? Now remember Chriſts rule; <hi>Whatſoever you would that men ſhould do unto you, even ſo do you unto them: for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely I ſhall ſpeak one word to that, which you call to witneſſe ſome of us to be lyars openly in Pulpits; becauſe that will turn the lye upon your ſelves. That is <hi>Dry Baptiſme:</hi> that was once publickly mentioned in a Pulpit, to be amongſt you. Now pray tell me (if you may not give it that name) what name do you give to this ordinance practiſed amongſt you? inſtead of baptizing an Infant, to pray over it onely, and to give it a name without the uſe of any water, either by dipping or ſprinkling, tell me (I ſay) I ſhall be glad to be informed by you, what do you call this ordinance? where is your ground for it? your primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inſtitution which you profeſſe to ſtick to? Is this orderly or diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly walking, I dare be ſo bold to ſay, that this hath no ground in Scripture either from rule or practice, precept or preſident, from Chriſt or his Apoſtles; nor in any of the Churches of Chriſt, till theſe late times, which every day (like <hi>Africa)</hi> bring forth ſome new Monſter: yet that this hath been lately practiſed amongſt you, will be made good to your faces, by thoſe who were eye and ear witneſſes: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you need not to take ſo much ſnuff at this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> place you ſay, you cannot but diſlike our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning of the Saints meeting to communicate to each other of the things of God, being as clear a command of Chriſts under the Goſpel, as any other: but (you ſay) we diſcountenance the practice, that we may keep men in ignorance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here's another groſſe ſlander: when will this mouth of lyes be ſtopped? did you ever hear any of us diſlike or diſown the meeting of Saints, to communicate to each other the things of God? when or where did we ever diſcountenance ſuch a practice? who <note n="*" place="margin">See I am. 4, 11, 12.</note> are you that you dare judge other men thus? as to ſay it is our endeavour and practice,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117654:18"/> to keep men in ignorance and blindneſſe, can you anſwer this to God? The Lord will one day judge you for this judging, and you will have the ſame meaſure meted to you: are you the men that call your meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings the meetings of Saints? look upon every branch of your rayling Paper, and deal truly with your own ſouls, judge your ſelves, that ye may not be condemned; doth any part of it ſavour of a Saints ſpirit, or of the things of God? if this be Saintſhip, the Devil is a Saint, he is a lyar, a rayler, a falſe accuſer, the accuſer of the brethren; and whether there be not much of theſe things in your invective, I leave it to God, and to the world to judge; ye make it appear to the world in it, what ſpirit ye are of, and what Saints ye are.</p>
               <p>Again, for the meeting of Saints, for thoſe ends you ſpeak of, I here tell you again, that we do own it, countenance it, exhort to it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, practiſe it; but what we diſlike, and muſt diſown, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our people from, that I likewiſe tell you, <hi>viz:</hi> The following after thoſe, who <hi>(having a form of godlineſſe) creep into houſes, and lead cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſilly women, laden with ſins, and led away with divers luſts.</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 5, 6. Again, we call to them to <hi>mark thoſe which cauſe diviſions and offences, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine which they have learned, and to avoid them. For they that are ſuch, ſerve not the Lord Jeſus, but their own bellies, and by good words, and fair ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> Rom. 16. 17, 18. Again, we call to them to remember Chriſts words, and to take his counſell, <hi>If any man ſhall come unto you, and ſay, Lo here is Chriſt, or there: beleeve it not. For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in ſo much that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very elect. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if they ſhall ſay unto you, Behold, he is in the deſart, go not forth: Behold, he is in the ſecret chambers, beleeve it not.</hi> Matth. 24. 23, 24. 26. We call to our people to remember the Apoſtle <hi>Peters</hi> words, who tels us, that as <hi>there were falſe Prophets amongſt the Jews, there ſhall be falſe teachers amongſt us, which ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, that many ſhall follow their pernicious wayes; by reaſon of whom the way of truth ſhall be evill ſpoken of: And through covetouſneſſe ſhall they with feigned words make merchandiſe of you;</hi> Theſe he deſcribes to be ſuch as <hi>deſpiſe government. Proſumptu us are they, ſelf-willed, they are not afraid to ſpeak evill of dignities.</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 1, 2, 3, and 10. verſes. Again, we deſire them to remember the counſell and direction of St. <hi>Jude,</hi> who <hi>exhorts the Saints to contend earneſtly for the faith, that was once de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ivered to the Saints. For</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>there are certain men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this condemnation.</hi> He likewiſe does de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them to be men that <hi>deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evill of dignities;</hi> that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117654:19"/> they are <hi>wanding ſtarres,</hi> that they are <hi>mockers:</hi> and <hi>theſe are they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſeparate themſelves; ſenſuall, having not the Spirit.</hi> If you call this a diſowning of the Saints meetings, to communicate to each other the things of God, a diſcouraging of others from them, and diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Saints practiſe, we leave it to God, Angels and men, to judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and us. And truly ſeeing theſe are thoſe laſt times, in which there are many Antichriſts abroad, as St. <hi>John,</hi> 1 Ep: 2. Ch: 18. I know not any counſell that can be more ſeaſonable to you your ſelves then this, if the Lord would give you hearts to receive and embrace it.</p>
               <p>Your 12th. branch is very large, a great deal of Riffraff raked up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to make one dunghill: much of the ſame ſtuffe that hath been ſpoken to before; the fruits of that ſpirit that reigns in the Saints of theſe times: I ſhall paſſe by, and turn over (as I promiſed you) all your raylings and revilings, and ſhall endeavour to anſwer a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l that deſerves an Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the beginning, you cannot but wonder, you ſay, at our contradictions, in that we would make the world beleeve, that we are like to ſuffer the loſſe of all, and to be brought to priſons, nay ſtakes, for our conſciences, by the Sectaries; and yet condemne them at the ſame time, for endeavouring a prodigious tolleration of all Religions: what a ſtrange contradiction is here (ſay you.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Have ye not read the ſtory in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 13. how <hi>Jeroboam</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered all the people of Iſrael to go a whoring after the Calves which he erected at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> and that when the man of God came out of <hi>Judah</hi> to cry againſt his Altar upon which he offered to his Calves, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> ſtretched out his hand againſt him, and cryed out, <hi>Lay hold on him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We need not uſe many arguments to make the world beleeve, that we are like to ſuffer the loſſe of all, to be brought to Priſons, and Stakes, and that for our conſciences: The world ſees it ſufficiently; that ſome of us have already been brought to priſons, and ſome are now in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; (and this not without loſſe) and all have been threatned, (if not with ſtakes) yet with as cruell deaths, and all this onely for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
               <p>Again on the other fide, that there is a Tolleration of all Religions endeavoured, Heaven and Earth do ſee; and ſurely this is prodigious, and we may here cry out, as the Lord by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Be aſtoniſhed, Oye heavens, at this, and be ye horribly afraid, be ye very deſolate, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Now if you will wonder; wonder not that we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117654:19"/> ſpeak of ſuch contradictions, when ye ſee ſuch contradictions acted: wonder at theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> But you undertake in the next place to juſtifie theſe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, where you poſitively ſay, that we are (indeed) of no religion, and ſo not to be tollerated by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Doth this ſound like the charity of Saints? you are of no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; let me a little look upon your names that have ſubſcribed this: <hi>Thomas Clutterbuck, William Burge, Giles Handcox, Thomas Sheapheard, Caleb Self,</hi> &amp;c.—one while you ſay we are Antichriſtian, here we are of no Religion: neither we nor our people, nor our Churches can in this eſtate be judged to be ſo much as Chriſtians. What can any Devill in Hell ſay worſe againſt us then this? if we denyed the true God, and whom he hath ſent Jeſus Chriſt, if we denied every Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith; if we were the moſt damned Hereticks under Heaven, what could you ſay more of us then this, that we are indeed of no Religion? you <hi>Thomas,</hi> or <hi>William,</hi> or <hi>Giles,</hi> will you make this good to any one of us, that we are of no Religion? Certainly this uncharitableneſſe is above all example monſtrous: Calumnies invented by Pagans againſt Chriſtians have not been ſo horrible: It could hardly have been imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Devil himſelf, had been able to have led any reaſonable creatures, into ſuch an exceſſe of impudency and ſlander, unto ſuch unchriſtian-like reproaches; yet theſe men would fain be accounted, <hi>The Saints.</hi> Well, take heed leſt while you run on in theſe wayes, you hear old <hi>Jacobs</hi> words; <hi>Curſed be their wrath, for it was feirce; and their rage, for it was cruell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Again, you are of no Religion (which indeed is true.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Freinds; have ye not heard of, nor read the ſtories of <hi>John of Leyden, Kinpperdollin,</hi> and <hi>David George?</hi> Thoſe famous (or rather infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous) Anabaptiſts, and of the pranks they play'd in <hi>Germany:</hi> and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord ſuffered Satan to lead thoſe proud hypocrites; who in their own eyes were ſuch holy Saints, as they could not but (in the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of their conſciences) ſeparate from the beſt reformed Churches of Chriſt (as being of no Religion) how they apoſtatized from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſervice, which the Scripture preſcribed, how they did put away baptiſme, the Lords Supper, and the preaching of the Word; and perſwaded many poore ignorant people, to follow their pernicious wayes, to their deſtruction, drawing them along after the directions of theſe new Prophets? have ye not heard of theſe things? whether or no the ſame ſpirit which was the author of that Anabaptiſme (and under
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117654:20"/> that of all other their prodigious and horrible impieties in <hi>Germany)</hi> doth not now make his appearance in <hi>England,</hi> and walk amongſt us, I leave to all to judge, who have but half an eye open, and are any whit acquainted with thoſe ſtories:—out of pitie and compaſſion, and meer love to your ſouls, the Lord knows) I beg and pray for you, that you be not taken captive in thoſe ſnares.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Again you are of no Religion (which indeed is true.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of no Religion? we acknowledge the onely true God, Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, for our God, and he hath acknowledged us to be his people, he hath taken us into Covenant with him; we beleeve that he hath given his Son Jeſus Chriſt to dye for our ſins, and that he is riſen again for our juſtification; we enjoy union and communion with him in grace here, being ſpiritually, and myſtically (yet really and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably) joyned to Chriſt as our Head and Husband; we pertake of the virtue of his mediation, in our juſtification, adoption, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we live in expectation of everlaſting communion, with our head Chriſt Jeſus, in that glory of heaven, the firſt fruits of which glory with Chriſt, is communicated to us in this life, as we are members of him, our head, and ſo in him are intereſſed in that glory which he is fully poſſeſt of; And as an earneſt thereof, we enjoy the ſence of Gods love, peace of conſcience, joy in the holy Ghoſt, and hope of glory: and whileſt we continue here in this life, in the communion of Saints, the Lord hath given us the preſence, the help, and ſupport of his own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to teach, guide, direct and enable us to, and to ſupport us in his worſhip, fear and ſervice, which we deſire and endeavour to perform, according to that rule which he hath given us for our faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his holy Word.</p>
               <p>All this, and yet of no Religion? if you have apoſtatized from this, I would fain know, what new religion you have found out; what God ye acknowledge, and after what way, and in what manner ye do wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: you tell me ſomething in the following part of this branch of your Paper, that after that way which we call hereſie, you ſo worſhip the God of your fathers; you have been lately taught to ſay this in a Sermon of your new Paſtors; I ſee you can remember the text. But I tell you (and will make it good to you) that if you worſhip the God of your fathers after that way which we call hereſie, your worſhip is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe in the devils noſtrils, and an abomination to the Lord. And this I doubt not but you will be convinc'd of anon, when I come to ſhew you what way 'tis that we call hereſie.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:117654:20"/>
               <p> Pray be ſo charitable for the time to come, as to think, that we are of ſome religion; though (it may be) not of yours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You ſay in the next place, that we are a hodg-podge made up of all like the <hi>Turks Alcoran,</hi> of Heatheniſme in permitting meer Atheiſts and prophane ones to be members of our Church, and partakers of our Seals in worſhip, of Jewiſh Tithes and oblations, of Popiſh ordination and ceremonies, of Epiſcopall pomp, pride, and avarice, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> What can you leave off ſo ſoon? is this all? have ye no more? 'tis wonder, but let's ſee what all this out-cry is for.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we are a meer hodge-podge; I would that you who pretend ſo to excell in Saint-ſhip and the Spirit, would but once diſcover, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt thus much, that ye had learn'd common civility, and how to give ſome civill language.</p>
               <p>In what are we an hodge-podge? you ſay we admit of heathens, and prophane ones, to be members of our Church, and partakers of the Seals of our worſhip.—Truly no other Heathens, nor prophane ones, then ſuch as you your ſelves are: I know of no Atheiſts, nor Heathens, that have been admitted members (as Atheiſts and Heathens) to any of our Churches, or any Church in Chriſtendome: it may be that ſome of you that charge us with this have been travellers, and ſo may lye by authoritie, (according to the Proverb) pray tell me, let's be informed by you a little, where, or in what particular Church of ours have any Atheiſts or Heathens been admitted members, or to either of the Seals? are any admitted to the firſt or ſecond Seal, but ſuch as are born within the line of the Church, of Chriſtian parents, profeſſing faith in Chriſt Jeſus? are any but ſuch admitted (by us) to the firſt Seal? or any but ſuch to the ſecond? Now will you make thoſe, that are born within the line of the viſible Church, and that do profeſſe faith in Chriſt Jeſus to be Heathens and Atheiſts? what Browniſticall, Anabaptiſticall tenets are theſe? wil not all the world that hears of this, hiſſe at your madnes, your ſimplicitie, and non-ſence, and your witleſſe, groundleſſe uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable charging and cenſuring of us?</p>
               <p>Again, where can you ſhew any meerly prophane ones, who conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing openly ſuch; without profeſſion of godly ſorrow, and deſires of coming to the Lord Jeſus for forgiveneſſe, and for increaſe of grace, that they might be inabled to lead a more holy life for the time to come, that have been admitted by us to the Lords Supper? This is as very a ſlander as all the reſt: and if they do deſire to come in this way, I would fain know of you, where is your warrant, and authoritie from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117654:21"/> Scripture to deny them? To ſatisfie you further in this; I long to ſee, where your rule, or your command is from Chriſt, to require ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by convincing Arguments, of the true grace of every Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: I am confident of it, that if that were ſtrictly ſtood upon by your new Paſtor, he would have but a thin Church, I am afraid (were an honeſt and ſufficient, impartiall underſtand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtian to be Judge of this) the greateſt part of the Ten Subſcribers would be found tardy in this, and ſo not fit to be members, (what ever you lay claim to)—What ever your new guide pretends to, he muſt ſtretch his tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, in diſpencing with, and in taking many upon charitable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in this point, or elſe his quarters would quickly grow as cold, and as thin at <hi>Cirenceſter,</hi> as they have been at other places, and ſo he muſt again turn Traveller, and an Itinerary.</p>
               <p>Again, I ſee you do not know (poore men) and therefore I would have you to go to your ſpirituall and gifted man to teach you, what is the nature of a viſible Church; and (leſt he ſhould be ignorant of it) I will give you a hint or two of it: The viſible Church, it is ſuch a body whoſe members are never all gracious (if you will beleeve the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) it is not like the Church inviſible, the Church of the Elect: but it is an Heterogeneous body (do you underſtand that word?) I'le help you, the parts of it are very diſſimular; ſome chaff, ſome corn, ſome wheat, ſome tares, a net of fiſhes good and bad, an houſe wherein are veſſels of honour and diſhonour; a fold of ſheep and goats; a tree of green and withered branches, a table of gueſts ſome with, ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a wedding garment: In a word, every viſible Church is a ſociety, wherein many are called, and few are choſen. Except therefore you will alter the nature of all true viſible Churches whereof the Scripture ſpeaks, we muſt grant, and ſo muſt you, that in every viſible Church, there are ſome members which have not true grace. If you have any thing to ſay to this, let me hear your Arguments, and I ſhall anſwer you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your next grounds upon which you ſay we are of no religion, are, becauſe we receive Jewiſh Tithes and Oblations; becauſe of Popiſh ordination and ceremonies, Epiſcopall pomp, pride and avarice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For matter of Tithes you give me large occaſion by and by after, and therefore I will refer that till I come to it there: Though your Paper be full of Tautologies, to ſtuffe up your invective, I ſhall ſhovell up as much of your filth as I can together, into order in my Anſwer.</p>
               <p>For Popiſh ordination, if therefore Popiſh becauſe by Biſhops, I have
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117654:21"/> likewiſe formerly ſaid enough alreadie to ſatisfie reaſonable men, (though perhaps not you) and therefore I ſhall ſay no more of that here neither.</p>
               <p>For Popiſh Ceremonies, we renounce them, and are as far as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeſt Anabaptiſt of you all, from tollerating them, either in our ſelves or others, where we may in a lawfull way hinder and remove them—For our Epiſcopall pomp, pride and avarice, which you ſay is in us; I tell you again you will be judging till you are judged, if you leave not the ſooner: The Lord forgive you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> To paſſe by much of your rubbiſh; the next thing you give me occaſion to take notice of is—your zeal againſt evill in opinion, and practiſe, againſt all humane inventions in the worſhip of God, and for the truth once delivered to the Saints; And here you (very well) put in a parentheſis (ſo far as the Lord ſhall diſcover it to you.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here I cannot but commend your zealous profeſſion; but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cannot but tell you plainly, that yet the Lord hath not diſcovered that truth to you which was once delivered to the Saints, or elſe you have ſhut your eyes, that you will not ſee it. For were your eyes open, and were you but clear ſighted, you muſt needs fall firſt upon your ſelves if you look diſcerningly into your wayes, and into your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, here declared in this your Paper; if you will bring theſe to the Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>viz:</hi> the written Word, you will finde abundance of evill both of opinion and practice, which tends rather to the ſubverting, then the defending and maintaining of the truth once delivered to the Saints. The Lord diſcover it to you, for men are very blear-ey'd and dim-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when they look upon their own wayes: <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us that <hi>every way of man is right in his own eyes:</hi> Prov. 21. 2. <hi>Said we not well, thou art a Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, and haſt a devill,</hi> ſaid the Jews to Chriſt: but I ſay let you and I lay by our ſelves, and let us bring our wayes and worſhip, our opinions and practiſes to that text in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20. <hi>To the Law, and to the teſtimonies: and if they ſpeak not according to this word, there is no light in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you tell me, you are reſolved (the ſame power aſſiſting you) that if I or any other (as we have done) do or ſhall vent any opinion, or hold any practiſe contrary to what is held forth in the Word of God, in the ſimplicitie of its own ſence and ſpirituall meaning, that we ſhall hear of it, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt I muſt here reprove you again for a falſhood, and a baſe ſlander, in that you ſay I have vented, and do hold any opinion or practice contrary to what is held forth in the Word: if we vent any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117654:22"/> thing (ſay you) as you have done: I challenge you and all the world to make that good; or if you do not, or at leaſt cannot, then be aſhamed and repent, acknowledge your fault, elſe you will be ſeen and known to the world to be ſuch as you are.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if when I do vent or hold any ſuch opinion or practice, you will be as good as your word and promiſe; <hi>viz.</hi> to let me hear of it: I profeſſe ſeriouſly to you, I will thank you for it; but let it be done then in a more civill Chriſtian-like way then this is; leave off rayling and ſlandering, and I ſhall ſay as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 141. 5. <hi>Let the righteous ſmite me, and it ſhall be a kindneſſe: and let him reprove me, and it ſhall be an excellent oil, which ſhall not break my head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third place, if any thing be vented contrary to what is held forth in the Word of God, in the ſimplicitie of its own ſence and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meaning, then I ſhall hear of it.—</p>
               <p>I ſay again I deſire it; But pray tell me, who ſhall be judge of the ſame ſence and ſpirituall meaning of the Word in its ſimplicitie? will you be Judges? Alas you are not fit, you can go no farther then the letter, and where the place requires more then a literall expoſition to ſet forth its meaning, you muſt be at a ſtand: And I am much miſtaken, if your new Paſtor can help you; as ſpirituall a man as you take him to be, I am ſure where you ſtumble upon ſome places, and do venture to give the meaning of them (your Paper ſhews) you ſomtimes miſtake fouly, and do make good that place of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16. where he ſaith, that <hi>in the Epiſtles of Paul there be ſome things hard to be underſtood, which they that are unlearned and unſtable, do wreſt, (as they do alſo the other Scriptures) unto their deſtruction.</hi> And if you fly to the old ſhift of the new lights of theſe times, and tell us that the Spirit will help you: I anſwer, firſt, 'tis the Spirit of God alone that muſt help you (if any ſpirit) to underſtand it's own ſpirituall meaning; And I muſt plainly tell you, that there be but few of the foot-ſteps of the Spirit of God to be ſeen (in this your Paper) if thoſe who are beſt acquainted with them, were to ſearch for them here.</p>
               <p>Again, the Spirit doth not now help by miraculous wayes, (as it hath done) by immediate revelations and infuſions, and by giving men the gifts of tongues, to underſtand all languages, (as in the Apoſtles times) and they that pretend to ſuch things in theſe times, are led along, and ſeduced by a lying ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place: you ſay, you truſt God will give you cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and boldneſſe to maintain the truth, by ſound doctrine; and to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117654:22"/> convince all gainſayers (though never ſo ſophiſticall) that ye ſhall not need to uſe (as ſome do) indirect means, as ſtirring up the Magiſtrate againſt them, there being no footſteps, for ſuch practice in the Goſpel to maintain the truth, but is the way of Antichriſt to ſet up his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 7. 15, 16. but the Saints overcome the devill and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments <hi>by the blood of the Lamb, and by the word of their teſtimony.</hi> Revel. 12. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, I know not what courage and boldneſſe God may give you to maintain the truth; but I am ſure Satan hath ſupplyed you with abundance of courage and boldneſſe (even to Impudencie) in ſpeaking evill of the way of truth, and in endeavouring to hold up errors: And what worthy Patrons ſuch as you are, are like to prove your ſelves to Truth, 'tis much to be ſuſpected if one view you well in that ſhape you appear in, in this your Invective.</p>
               <p>2ly, Whereas you ſay the Magiſtrate is an indirect means, that there are no footſteps of it in the Goſpel, that 'tis the way of Antichriſt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. It may be you have a means that's more direct in your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celt then by the ſword of the Magiſtrate; though it hath fewer footſteps in the Goſpel, and that is by the Sword of the Souldier.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Paper. </seg>
                  </label> But I know you expect I ſhould ſay ſomething here (becauſe you give the occaſion) concerning the power of the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel; The power of the Magiſtrate (in maintaining truth) (you ſay) hath no footſteps in the Goſpel, 'tis an Antichriſtian way:—Did I not tell you in the beginning how exceedingly a carnall heart loves libertie, and freedome? Oh, 'tis a ſweet morſell, how paſſionately do men purſue it? every coercive and vindictive power that would reſtrain it, and puniſh it's wickedneſſe; oh this is an Antichriſtian way. And to prove this, you urge, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 7. 15, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. Now you ſpeak like your ſelves: Heres the pure pute language of all the Anabaptiſts that I ever yet heard or read of, or have ſpoken with.—I doubt not but to make it appear to you, that theſe are onely the fancies and devices of Phanaticall Enthuſiaſts (and not to be deduced from Scriptures) who becauſe they be diſſolute would have no bonds of Laws; becauſe they are Schiſmaticks, would have no diſcipline in the Church; and becauſe they walk inordinately, they would have no coercive power of the Magiſtrate to reſtrain them. This is onely the ſpirit of thoſe Schiſmaticall Teachers, who under a pretence of ſpirituall freedome, will lead you into all carnall libertie, prophaneneſſe, ſacriledge, and faction.—And have they (nor you)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117654:23"/> nothing elſe to prove Magiſtracie to be Antichriſtian, and to have no footſteps in the Goſpel, but <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 7. 15. 16. Poore men, did not I tell you but now, what miſerable Expoſitors, and applyers, and wreſters of Scripture you were, to your own deſtruction? will you ſee how ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous you are in this place, and how ſimply and ſinfully you abuſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. The text alledged plainly ſhews, that power was given to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt to wage warre with the Saints, and by his Armies to overcome them; and this you bring to prove, that the Sword of Juſtice in the hand of the Civill Magiſtrate under the Goſpel is Antichriſtian; oh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ignorance and impudence; he that thus teacheth you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and apply Scriptures, is a blinde leader of the blinde, and (if the Lord open not your eyes the ſooner) you will both fall into the ditch.</p>
               <p>Again, you urge, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. 11. where the text ſaith, that the Saints overcame Satan <hi>by the blood of the Lambe, and the word of their teſtimony:</hi> and this you bring to prove, that the Power of the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel in reſtraining and puniſhing errors, and maintaining truth, is an indirect and an Antichriſtian way: may not he that hath but half an eye ſee how groſly abſurd you are in theſe things? The plain mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the place is no more then this, That by the death and ſufferings of Jeſus Chriſt (the Lambe of God ſlain) the devill and all his Angels, all the enemies of mans ſalvation, are overcome; and the Saints are ſaid to overcome him by his blood, as they have their garments waſht in the blood of the Lambe, as they are juſtified and ſanctified by his blood, and by his Word; the victory of Chriſt over the devill and his Angels being obtained not in his own name, but for us; we (that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in his blood, and the word of his teſtimony) are ſaid (in him) to have overcome Satan, and his Angels, the enemies of our ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Do you ſee now how ſimply you have quoted Scripture here, and how little to your purpoſe? Surely this is no ſmall fin, thus to abuſe and wreſt the Word and the truth of God, to the maintaining of errors; therefore repent for it.</p>
               <p>Again you ſay, the power of the Magiſtrate under the Goſpel is an Antichriſtian way,—and you have fairly prov'd it;—Let me tell you, juſt thus did <hi>John of Leyden</hi> in <hi>Munſter,</hi> all Power of the Magiſtrate amongſt Chriſtians, was by him and his followers cry'd down as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, and perſecution of tender conſciences; till he himſelf had gained power by his ſeduced ones, to murther and baniſh all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in <hi>Munſter;</hi> and <hi>John</hi> himſelf was got up into the Throne of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, made, and proclaimed by them his followers to be King of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117654:23"/> the new Jeruſalem in <hi>Munſter,</hi> where he exerciſed a great deal of moſt barbarous and unheard of cruelty; and then Magiſtracie was no longer Antichriſtian, when the Saints there (as they call'd themſelves) were once become Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>I onely minde you of this ſtory, becauſe the Town and Countrey <note place="margin">Note that <hi>Giles Hancox</hi> one of the Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hath (ſince this) taken his Oath for Iuſtice of the Peace, and now executes that office in Ciren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</note> ſpeaks it, that ſome of you that have here ſubſcribed Magiſtracie to be Antichriſtian, are deſigned and appointed, and are ready to undertake the office of being Magiſtrates among your neighbours; I hope when you your ſelves come to be Magiſtrates and Juſtices, then Magiſtracie will no longer be accounted Antichriſtian amongſt you, when the Sword is once in the Saints hands.</p>
               <p>But that I may not diſcourage you in your young undertakings, I will take a little pains to inform your ignorance; and to ſhew you what foot-ſteps the Magiſtrates executing of Juſtice upon tranſgreſſors (both againſt the firſt and ſecond Table) hath in the Goſpel. I hope I ſhall make it appear plainly to you, that 'tis ſo farre from being Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that it is Gods own ordinance, and that under the Goſpel; and you ſhall ſee 'tis onely ignorance, that makes you ſo impudent, as to ſay, that this hath no foot-ſteps in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place; let me tell you, that all the beſt reformed Churches in Chriſtendome, do renounce and deteſt theſe Anabaptiſticall dreams of yours; and moſt harmoniouſly and willingly confeſſe, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, to be Gods will that the world be governed by Laws (by the way remember that the Church is within the Common-wealth;) and God himſelf hath appointed the Civill Magiſtrate, and hath delivered to him, the Sword, to the protection and praiſe of good men; and for puniſhment on the evill. And by this bridle, mens vices and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhould be reſtrained, whether committed againſt the firſt or againſt the ſecond Table.</p>
               <p>2ly, They confeſſe the Power and Authoritie of Magiſtrates to be the ordinances of God himſelf, appointed, as well to the manifeſtation of his own glory, as to the ſingular profit of mankinde: That by reaſon of the will of God himſelf revealed in his Word, we muſt not onely ſuffer, and be content that they ſhould rule, but alſo to love them, fear them, and withall reverence, and honour, and embrace them as the Embaſſadors and Miniſters of the moſt high God (being in his ſtead, and preferr'd for the good of their Subjects) that we ſhould poure out prayers for them, pay tributes to them; and in all buſineſſes of the Common-wealth (which are not againſt the Word of God) to obey their Laws and Edicts.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:117654:24"/>
               <p> 3ly, They beleeve alſo, and do willingly acknowledge, that every lawfull Magiſtrate being by God himſelf conſtituted, the keeper and defender of both Tables of the Law, may and ought, firſt and chiefly, to take care of Gods glory, and (according to his place) to preſerve Religion, when pure, and to reſtore it when decayed and corrupted; and to this end, to reſtrain and puniſh, as well Atheiſts, Blaſphemers, Hereticks, and Schiſmaticks, as the violaters of Juſtice and Civill peace.</p>
               <p>Now by what ſpirit you are led, to run out of, and to cry down the opinions and practiſes, of all the Churches of Chriſt in this point, as Antichriſtian, every man may judge: And the Lord help you timely to ſee whither you are running headlong; not onely beyond the Churches of Chriſt; but into ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urdities and extremities, which even the Law of Nature teaches poore Pagans and Heathens to avoid, who have their Governors and government amongſt them: nay even to be more bruitiſh, and more void of underſtanding then the creature, the very beaſts that periſh, for even they too, are taught of nature to obſerve an order amongſt themſelves.—But to ſhew it unto you from Scripture grounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> To ſtir up the Magiſtrate againſt thoſe who oppoſe the truth, you ſay is an indirect way, that hath no foot-ſteps in the Goſpel, but is Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, let me preſent you a glaſſe wherein you may ſee your own faces drawn to the life. In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. and St. <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle, theſe two (ſpeaking of falſe prophets that were then in thoſe dayes; and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewing what ones ſhould creep into the Church) do ſo deſcribe them that all men may ſee them: <hi>They walk</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) after the fleſh, in the luſts of uncleanneſſe, and deſpiſe government and dominion. Preſumptuous are they, ſelf-willed: they are not afraid to ſpeak evill of dignities; Whereas Angels, which are greater in power and might, bring not a ray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing accuſation againſt them before the Lord.</hi> So St. <hi>Jude,</hi> 8. ver. <hi>Theſe filthy dreamers defile the fleſh, deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evill of dignities.</hi> If you note it; theſe words of theſe Apoſtles do as directly fit the Anabaptiſts of theſe times, as if they had aymed at them.—This by the way.</p>
               <p>In the next place: Ple ſhew you out of Scripture, that the office of the Civill Magiſtrate, is ſo far from being Antichriſtian, that it is an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice appointed by God himſelf, for the adminiſtration of Juſtice, and preſervation of Peace both in Church and Common-wealth. And that in this way of adminiſtring Juſtice, and preſerving Peace in Church
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117654:24"/> and State, their authoritie extends, to the puniſhing and reſtraining of Hereticks, Blaſphemers, Schiſmaticks, as well as Murtherers and theeves: Firſt ſee theſe places of Scripture, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 20, 21, 22. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 6. and 11. ver. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. 15, 16. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 21. Theſe places will ſhew you ſufficiently, that Magiſtracie is Gods ordinance. If you would have a Goſpel proof, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 6 firſt verſes, where they are call'd ſeverall times, <hi>The ordinance of God,</hi> and <hi>the miniſters of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2ly, You ſhall ſee it cleared to you <hi>(de fact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>)</hi> that theſe Magiſtrates have exerciſed their power, in ſuppreſſing errors, hereſies and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which have been contrary to ſound doctrine and true Religion. See 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15. 13. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 11, 24. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23. 20. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
               <p>3ly, You ſhall ſee that they did exerciſe this power <hi>(de jure</hi> too) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gods warrant, and by virtue of his ordination: See <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. from the 5. to the 10. ver. and 17. Chap. 2, 3, 4, 5, ver. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 20. <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. 16.</p>
               <p>All that you can ſay to this is, that theſe be old Teſtament texts, and God appointed Magiſtrates under the Law, and the Jews were kept in order by them; yet this doth not prove that Chriſtians under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel may exerciſe that power one over another, or that they need any Civill Magiſtrate.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. I ſhall ſhew you the weakneſſe and ſimplicitie of this reply, and that in this order.—Firſt, there is the like neceſſity of the Civill Magiſtrates and Judges under the Goſpel, as well as under the Law; for the ſad experience of theſe times ſhews us, and the Scripture ſhews us, that the ſame diſorders fall out amongſt Chriſtians, as did among the Jews; not onely <hi>envyings, ſtrifes, debates, going to law,</hi> &amp;c. and the like diſorders in the State, but alſo <hi>errors, hereſies, and blaſphemies, and diviſions in the Church.</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 3. and Chap. 6. 6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 18. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now if there be the ſame diſorders in Church and State (amongſt Chriſtians) as were among them; it muſt neceſſarily follow (and you cannot but in reaſon grant,) that here's need of the ſame power and au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horitie for the reſtraining and puniſhing of theſe.—If we have need of the ſame power and authoritie, and that hath been a power appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God for the ſame end, if you will deny it to us under the Goſpel, you muſt ſhew me, where ever that Command and ordinance was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, or that pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce prohibited, under the new Teſtament. I muſt confeſſe to you that I could never yet finde it repeall'd or prohibited by Chriſt or his Apoſtles; and therefore rationall men muſt grant that it ſtands ſtill in force under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And to ſatisfie you further, I will ſhew you ſeverall grounds why,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117654:25"/> and places from which you muſt conclude, that their Calling is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable by, and agreeable to the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we having need of ſuch, as well as the Jews under the Law, you muſt either grant us them, or elſe you muſt conclude, that the State of the Church of Chriſt (in reſpect of the Civill Magiſtrate) is worſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Teſtament then is was under the old, which no man will be ſo mad as to ſay.</p>
               <p>Again, if the office of the Magiſtrate, were an office and ordinance under the Law, and not under the Goſpel, then it muſt be becauſe this ordinance was ceremoniall and typicall; but this cannot be: for I ſhall plainly ſhew you that the power of the Magiſtrate is morall and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall.</p>
               <p>Firſt look upon the fift Commandment, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. I hope you will not turn Antinomians too, and deny the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of the ten Commandments: if you do, the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> words will ſhew, that if you condemne all the reſt, yet this Command is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and perpetuall; for he renews it in the Goſpel; and it muſt ſtand as long as the Goſpel ſtands. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6. 1, 2. Now I beleeve that your inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſpirituall Paſtor will not deny, but that in that Command (though the Apoſtle applyes it there onely to parents and children) yet both this relate and correlate, <hi>viz:</hi> the Magiſtrate and Subject, the power and authoritie of the one, and the obedience and ſubmiſſion of the other, are both warranted and commanded.</p>
               <p>Again, the power of the Magiſtrate muſt needs be morall and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall in the Church; becauſe the reaſon, and ground, and end of that power is morall and perpetuall: one ground and reaſon why that power was eſtabliſht amongſt the Jews, was becauſe ſeducers and drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of dreams, would turn away the hearts of Gods people from the Lord; and the end of exerciſing and executing that power, was that all Iſrael might fear, and do no more ſo wickedly, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 5. 11. Now theſe grounds, reaſons and ends of the ordaining the power at firſt, and the executing of it are perpetuall, and are at this time amongſt us, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot be denyed (by reaſonable men) but that the power muſt be ſtill in force: you know that the grounds, and reaſons, and ends of both the inſtitution of it, and the execution of it are now with us, <hi>viz:</hi> ſeducers do ſtill indeavour to draw away the hearts of Gods people from the Lord (if Juſtice were executed on theſe) the people would fear, and do no more ſo wickedly.</p>
               <p>Again, you ſhall finde that the want of a Civill Magiſtrate to ſway
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117654:25"/> the Sword of Juſtice, was noted by the holy Ghoſt, as a great plague, and a fearfull judgement on the Jews: See <hi>Judg.</hi> 17. 6. and Chap. 18. 1. v. and 21. 25. So likewiſe on the contrary, 'twas fore-told and promiſed as a ſingular bleſſing to the Chriſtian Church under the Goſpel: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23. And Kings under the Goſpel are required and commanded to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their power to the advancement of Chriſts kingdom: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10, 11, 12. The Pſalm is clearly expounded of Chriſt and his kingdom by the Apoſtle, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 25. and <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 23. Now (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>Be wiſe, O ye kings; be inſtructed, O ye Judges: Serve the Lord with fear.</hi> Now ye muſt <note place="margin">Dr <hi>Featly</hi> in his Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per dipt.</note> know, that Kings and Judges, ſerve God two manner of wayes: Firſt, as men by leading a godly life agreeable to the rules of the Goſpel. 2ly, as Kings and Judges, they ſerve God by enacting and executing Laws with convenient ſeverity; commanding juſt things, and prohibiting evill: So did <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah:</hi> And then properly do Kings and Judges ſerve God as Kings and Judges, when they do thoſe things in and for the ſervice of God, which none can do but they.</p>
               <p>Farther yet, ye ſhall ſee, how in the Goſpel, Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles, have approved of the Authoritie of the Civill Magiſtrate, and have commanded obedience to them. <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 21. Chriſt commands all to pay unto <hi>Ceſar, the things that are Ceſars:</hi> And he himſelf payed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and acknowledged even <hi>Pilates</hi> power over him to be from God: <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. 11.—Again, the Apoſtle commands all people to ſubmit, and to obey the Magiſtrate, and to obey for the Lords ſake, and for that they are the ordinance of God. And therefore ſurely the Authority of the Magiſtrate is eſtabliſht by the Goſpel. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 4, 5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15. Again, the Apoſtle commands us to offer up prayers in ſpeciall for them as Magiſtrates: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>that we may leade a quiet and peaceable life,</hi> under them, <hi>in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</hi> Which we could not do, except the Lord bleſſe their government over us.</p>
               <p>May not a man now ſay to you here, as Chriſt did to the Phariſees, <hi>Ye erre, not knowing the Scriptures:</hi> what a groſſe error is this in you, to ſet your hands to ſuch a falſhood as this is? That the office of a Magiſtrate under the Goſpel is Antichriſtian, and hath no foot-ſteps in the Goſpel? Ye ſee it hath thoſe foot-ſteps there which neither you, nor all the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts in <hi>England,</hi> nor all the Devils in Hell, ſhall be able ever to raze out. The Lord give you underſtanding, that you may ſee your error, be aſhamed of it, and repent for it, and from it.</p>
               <p>Let's ſee what you ſay next:—Truly in 20 lines together, or more, nothing but a throwing out your very gaul, in moſt unchriſtianlike ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117654:26"/> and reproaches; in which too, the Divel hath holpen you, to belch out as helliſh lyes, as ever the father of lyes himſelf vented. Oh, what a Saint-lik ſpirit this ſavours of? to rayl, and brawl, and ſpeak evill of Magiſtrates and Miniſters, and all that come in your way. In your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing page of your Paper, ye pretend much to the carriage of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; you ſay you are commanded to be gentle, and meek, and curteous; to be moderate, to walk as brethren, and to beſeech men, and that you are condemned for following theſe; I leave it (even to your ſelves) and to all the world to judge, of the meekneſſe, and lambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſpirit, which you have in this Paper expreſt to be in you. I leave it upon your own conſciences (if they be not ſeared) if they be, the Lord ſoften them, and give you ſpeedily a ſence of your condition, (for my part) I ſhall beſeech God to pardon you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You call us vain, time-ſerving, ſelf-ſeeking Teachers, turning with every winde, perfidious men, who will be any thing, nay nothing for a little pelf, though under pretences of piety, penny maſters, hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, falſe prophets; that our means is the prop of our miniſtery. That we will not truſt God, that we are at every word of command from men; facing about, and turning as we were; that we have ſworn to maintain Epiſcopacy with &amp; cetera.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We ſhall not revile again, but, as I ſaid, commit our ſelves to God who judgeth righteouſly. We may ſay of you as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Copper-ſmith; you <hi>William,</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Caleb,</hi> &amp;c. you have done us much wrong, the Lord help other men to beware of you:—onely before I leave this, let me ask you one queſtion or two: Pray let me know ('tis but a reaſonable requeſt from you who have charged us with it) in what have you found us vain Teachers? hath our teaching been in vain to you? we are ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie for you; and ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>If our Goſpel be hid, 'tis hid to them that are loſt: In whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of them which beleeve not, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them. For we have not preached our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and our ſelves your ſervants for Jeſus ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, how many winds and times have you known us to turn withall? we have (the Lord knows) deſired, and we hope we have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto held faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wavering; and we truſt (through Chriſt that ſtrengthens us) that we ſhall yet ſtand faſt in the faith, and quit our ſelves like men, though we have ſtrong ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings: we bleſſe God, we have not as yet ſaid a confederacie, nor feared the fear of men.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:117654:26"/>
               <p> Again, which of us, and which way can you make it appear, that we are ſelf-ſeeking men? who amongſt us have for Pelf or honour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved perfidious to our truſt, and to our charges: we truſt that the Lord hath ſeen, that we have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, we do not ſeek our own, but every man an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others wealth, and the things which are Chriſt Jeſus. As <hi>Paul</hi> enjoyns, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 2. And for your parts (I think) you have as little cauſe or ground to charge us with this, as any, for in our labours to you wards, even to this day, we are able to ſay as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 14. <hi>We are ready to come again unto you, and we will not be burthenſome to you, for we ſeek not yours but you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, which of us can you charge (juſtly) with prophecying or preaching falſe things to you; name the men (if you can) that are falſe prophets, and prove it againſt us: we tell you again, that we are not of thoſe that handle the Word of God deceitfully; and we deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the hidden things of darkneſſe, and (we bleſſe God) we can ſay as <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. <hi>We have received of the Lord, that which we alſo have delivered unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, when, or where, or which of us have you known to be Beagles to our Reverend Patrons (as you call them) the Biſhops? where have we faced about, and turn'd again as we were? or whom amongſt us can you prove to have taken the Biſhops Oath with <hi>&amp; caetera:</hi> we are able to make your falſhood and ſlanders in this appear to the world; that in this County of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> it was generally oppoſed, and refuſed: how baſe then are theſe accuſations?</p>
               <p>Again, whom of us have you known to have layen at the Ale-houſe three dayes in a week?—bluſh for ſhame.—Did you know what you did, when you were led by the noſe, to ſet your hands to ſuch an heap of lyes together, which are all from the father of lyes; and any one of which we challenge you and all the world, to make good againſt us, if you can. Does it become the Saints to do ſuch things as theſe are? Me thinks, here be fit grounds for you, to be aſhamed and confounded in your ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you tell us, that certainly, if you ſhould ſee the downfall of our means, you ſhould ſee the downfall of our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, that being the grand prop thereof; And therefore rather then we will truſt God for our maintenance, we will take, nay force the legall maintenance of Tithes from the people, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, we know that the downfall of our Miniſtery is that which you look, and long, and gape after; that ſo you may run
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117654:27"/> on without controul, in your villanies. But (me thinks) (if you were not wilfully ignorant) you might know, that Tithes are not the grand prop of our Miniſtery. 'Tis a promiſe of Chriſt, that is the prop of it; And that is ſuch a prop, that the gates of hell ſhall never prevail againſt it: he hath promiſed to be with our Miniſtery (and us in our Miniſtery) to the end of the world; And therefore you are not like to ſee the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of it ſo ſoon as you think for: except you have a revelation (as one of your grand Prophets lately had) that the end of the world will be very ſoon; your hope in this (therefore) is but as the hope of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which ſhall periſh, and be as a ſpiders webb.</p>
               <p>If the Lord ſtrip us of that which you call legall maintenance, if he bring us to a morſell of bread, yea down to ſackcloth and aſhes, yet I doubt not, but you ſhall finde, that we ſhall truſt God ſo farre for our maintenance, that while we live we ſhall preach the Goſpel: And while we do preach the Goſpel, we doubt not but we ſhall live by the Goſpel: and if our maintenance be in that way which you call legall, we ſhall not deſire to keep it, if we be not able to juſtifie it to honeſter men, yea better wits then yours; to be lawfull, yea under the Goſpel. And that in the next place I ſhall undertake to ſhew you, by removing all thoſe ſilly and ridiculous objections which you (in your Paper) have layed in againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Firſt, you ſay, 'twas a legall maintenance. 2ly, that 'twas on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to the Prieſts under the Law for their ſervice. 3ly, that 'twas given to them as one of the ten Tribes, which they took onely of their brethren, and that not by compulſion; but (you ſay) there is no equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie that our Prieſts ſhould have it. Firſt, becauſe they are not the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth part of the people: 2ly, becauſe they have inheritance among their brethren. 3ly, (you ſay) the Prieſts of the Law had but the 10<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of the increaſe; ours of mens labours. 4ly, the Prieſts of the Law were not ſo covetous as ours be. 5ly, (you ſay) Chriſt having put an end to the Prieſthood, hath alſo changed the Law which (you ſay) is Tithes: here you urge, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 12. Hence you do farther inferre, that to take Tithes under the Goſpel, is abominable hereſie: and a denying of Chriſt come in the fleſh. 6ly, (you ſay) you may ſee God blaſting them in our poſterity, for they generally come to nothing, but are miſerable Laſtly, that in this we are Jewiſh, and may be call'd Jews.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For Anſwer. Firſt, whereas you ſay 'tis legall maintenance; this is juſt as you call repentance, humilitie, obedience, and all duties legall graces and duties. We need not value ſuch a brand ſet upon the office,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:117654:27"/> or Miniſtery, or maintenance of the miniſtery of the Goſpel, when the very graces of the Goſpel, ſuffer by you and your companions under the ſame reproach:—But to anſwer you.—'Tis legall maintenance, (ſay you) how legall? (I beleeve your meaning in this, is, that which you ſpeak more plainly in the 2d) as it was paid onely to Prieſts under the Law, therfore legall: if this be your meaning (as it can be no other) here I ſhall preſently ſhew you your groſſe ignorance: Were Tithes paid onely to Prieſts under the Law? how falſe is this? you might have ſeen in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. quoted by you, that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchiſede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h,</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> himſelf in <hi>Abrahams</hi> loins. Now the Apoſtle ſhews you that the prieſthood of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was not that of <hi>Levi;</hi> for this is taken away (ſaith he) but the order of <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Prieſthood abides for ever.</p>
               <p>Here then you ſee, that Tithes were paid to ſome other Prieſts then onely to the Prieſts under the Law. Farther—when you read that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> paid Tithes; I deſire to know from you, by what law they paid Tithes: whether was it by the Law of Nature, or by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viticall Law, or by an Evangelicall Law? one of the three muſt be, 'tis plain as the Sun, that it could not be by a Leviticall Law, and by virtue of that; for that was not then enacted, and by that Law <hi>Levi</hi> was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and not to pay Tithes; yet <hi>Levi</hi> himſelf in <hi>Abraham</hi> paid Tithes to <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi> Again, if they paid by the Law of Nature, that Law binds all men ſtill, as well now as then. And laſtly, if they paid by an Evangelicall Law, that binds alſo all Chriſtians to pay their Tithes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the maintenance of <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> prieſthood which endures for ever. Pray let me ſee your Anſwer to this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you ſay, Tithes were given to the Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, as they were one of the ten Tribes; which they took onely of their brethren, and that not by compulſion; but there's no equalitie that our Prieſts ſhould have it: firſt, becauſe they are not the hundredth part of the people: 2ly, they have inheritance among the brethren. Again, they had but the tenth of the increaſe: ours of mens labours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> In Anſwer to this, I muſt tell you here again your ignorance hath made you very bold and impudent, in ſpeaking that which I ſhall ſhew to you, and to al the world to be very falſe—And it muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe heads. You put me here upon the conſideration of theſe two things: firſt the proportion of the perſons of the Prieſts under the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and 2ly, the proportion of their maintenance, and to compare it with ours now.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:117654:28"/>
               <p> If you will look upon theſe two things in Scripture; you ſhall finde how falſly and abſurdly you do argue in your Paper. I will ſhew you, firſt for their perſons, that it will not be hard to prove, that the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> under the Law, were not the fourtieth part of the people. 2ly, for their maintenance, they had three times as much as any one Tribe.—</p>
               <p>Firſt for their perſons; look upon the numbring of them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> Exp: Pſal. 110. pag 477, 478, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 1. 46. with <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 39. and you ſhall finde, that the other Tribes were numbred from 20 yeers old and upward, to all that were able to bear Arms, which was to the age of fifty yeers (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) (for at that age they were ſuppoſed to be unſerviceable for war) and yet being thus numbred, but from 20 to 50 yeers, their number amounted to ſix hundred and three thouſand, five hundred and fifty men able to go to war. On the other ſide, the Levites were numbred from one month old and upward, and yet the whole number amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but to two and twenty thouſand. Now conjecture the number of thoſe in the other Tribes, who were under 20 yeers of age, and who were above fifty yeers to be but half as many as the reſt, (as it cannot be ſuppoſed that they were leſſe) yet the whole number of the Tribes reckoned from their infancie upward, will amount at leaſt to nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred two thouſand men, of which number, the number of the Levites, is juſt the one and fourtieth part. If you ſay that the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to a mighty number afterwards, as may be found, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 3. I ſay that the whole people increaſed accordingly; for the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> which was before but ſeventy foure thouſand, was then five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand, and in <hi>Jehoſaphats</hi> time eleven hundred thouſand: See 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 9. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17. latter end:—here then ye ſee, how ye are miſtaken in the proportion of the perſons of the Levites. They were ſo farre from being a tenth part, that they were not ſo much as the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part of the people. And in the next place look into the proportion of their maintenance, and you ſhall ſee your ſelves more miſtaken there, one would think that the fourtieth part of the people, could require but the fourtieth part of the maintenance in proportion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You ſay, they had no inheritance amongſt their brethren, and that they had but the tenth of the increaſe onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> How durſt you thus belye the Scriptures? do you do it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, or wilfully? Firſt you ſhall finde that they had the tenth of all the increaſe of ſeed, and fruit, and great and ſmall cattell. See <hi>Levit.</hi> 27. 30. and 32. ver. 2ly, though they were not the fourtieth part of the people, they had 48 Cities with ſuburbs for cattell, and for gardens.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117654:28"/> See <hi>Numb.</hi> 35. the 7 firſt verſes; which Cities were next to the beſt, and in many Tribes the beſt of all: in <hi>Judah,</hi> Hebron; in <hi>Benjamin,</hi> Gibeon; both royall Cities: ſo that thoſe Cities with about a mile ſuburbe to every one of them, can come to little leſſe then the wealth of one Tribe alone in that little Countrey, which from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> was but about 160 miles long.</p>
               <p>3ly, They had all the firſt-fruits both of clean and unclean beaſts; ſee <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 13. of the fruits of the earth, and of the fleece of the ſheep: <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 4. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10. 35. of men to be redeemed, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 15, 16.</p>
               <p>4ly, The meat-offerings, the ſiu-offerings, the treſpaſſe-offerings, the heave-offerings, and the wave-offerings were all theirs. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p>5ly, They had all vows and voluntary oblations, and conſecrations, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 8, 9.</p>
               <p>6ly, (excepting the Holocauſt) they had either the ſhoulder, or the breaſt, or the skin, or ſomething of every ſacrifice which was offered: <hi>Numb.</hi> 18. 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 3. <hi>Levit.</hi> 7. 30, 31.</p>
               <p>7ly, The males were to appear three times a yeer before the Lord, and they were not to come empty handed: <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 15: 17.—Laſtly, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them did belong many recompences of injuries, which was the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the principall, and a fift part. <hi>Num.</hi> 5. 7. 8. Now put the Tithes, the Cities, and theſe other conſtant revenues together, and you ſhall finde that the Prieſts and the Levites, who were but about a quarter as many as one Tribe, had yet about three times revenues of any one Tribe.</p>
               <p>And thus you may ſee how falſly, how blindly, and groundleſly you argue, from comparing the revenues and the numbers of the Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, with the Miniſters of the Goſpel and their Tithes. And whereas you ſay, they took it not by compulſion, how ſimple and ſilly is this? where did the people deny it? or where did they refuſe the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it? was it not a command of God? Doubtleſſe had there been denyall, there had been compulſion, in this as in other Laws.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your next objection againſt us, why we ſhould not receive Tithes, is becauſe we are covetous; we bring into our ſtore-houſes, but we do not give to the poore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I onely ask you here again how ye dare? how ye are not afraid to judge others thus: how came you to have that ſearching eye to look into mens hearts, and to ſee how covetous they are? Certainly (though ye pretend to beleeve what's written, in the Law, and the Prophets)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117654:29"/> your practiſe ſhews that you make little conſcience of making that your rule to walk by; or elſe you have learnt the trick of many now a dayes, to ſlip the collar, and to lay by ſo much of the Word, as doth in any way tend to the bridling or reſtraining of you in any of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly luſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you charge us with abuſing that place of Scripture, <hi>Mala.</hi> 3. 10. which (you ſay) was lawfull then, but not now; and you prove it thus: Chriſt having put an end to the Prieſthood, hath alſo changed the Law: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 12. which Law (you ſay) was Tithes. And hence you conclude, that to take Tithes under the Goſpel (there being not the leaſt ſyllable for it) is abominable hereſie, and a denying of Chriſt come in the fleſh, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, for your charging us with abuſe of Scripture, I may ſay to you as Chriſt to the Phariſees judging others, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 3. <hi>Why beholdeſt thou the moat in thy brothers eye, and conſidereſt not the beam that is in thine own eye? Thou hypocrite, firſt caſt out the beam out of thy own eye:—</hi>what a beam there is in the eye of your judgement, plainly appears to the world, in the very next line to this, in which you charge us with abuſing Scripture: And that is in your text cited, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 12. where the Apoſtle, ſaying, that the prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> being changed, there is of neceſſitie a change of the Law; you very boldly and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſay, that by the word <hi>Law</hi> there, the Apoſtle means Tithes; And hence you conclude, that the right of Tithes is changed;—abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance and abuſe of Scripture: If this be not that wreſting of the Scripture which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, let the underſtanding judge. Me thinks it would be incredible (if I had it not under your hands) that men who pretend ſo much to the ſpirit as you do, and are led by ſuch ſpirituall men, as you are, ſhould be thus blind.</p>
               <p>I'le take a little pains here too, to ſhew you the Apoſtles meaning, and your own groſſe miſtakes.</p>
               <p>The ſcope of the Apoſtle in ſeverall Chapters here, is onely to draw off the <hi>Hebrews</hi> from the ſacrifices of the Law, and from ſeeking perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them; and to bring them to Chriſt crucified (and offered up now a ſacrifice for the ſins of thoſe that beleeve in him) and to the ſeeking of perfection, juſtification, ſanctification, and life in him: To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Apoſtle ſets forth to them the excellency of Chriſts prieſthood and ſacrifice, above the prieſthood and ſacrifices of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi.</hi> In this Chapter he ſets forth the honour and excellency of Chriſts prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, above that of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> under the Law, by ſhewing, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:117654:29"/> of <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> prieſthood above that of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> (he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving avouched and declared before, that Chriſt was conſtituted and made a Prieſt for ever after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech)</hi> firſt here he ſhews that Chriſt is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec</hi> (as from a teſtimony of <hi>David</hi> in Chap. 5.) from that abſolute agreement betwixt <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedech</hi> and Chriſt, the parts wherof are theſe. 1. As <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was King and Prieſt of the moſt high God, ſo Chriſt. 2ly, as <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was King of righteouſneſſe, and Prince of peace, ſo was Chriſt. 3ly, As <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> his parents, kindred, beginning and ending of life are not recorded, ſo Chriſt as man without father, as God without mother, kindred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or ending of life, therefore Chriſt is truly a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech.—</hi>Secondly (having ſhew'd that Chriſt is a Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedec)</hi> he comes to ſhew that <hi>Melchiſedecs</hi> prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is more excellent then that of <hi>Levi</hi> (and then 'twill follow, that he who is a Prieſt after his order (as Chriſt is) is greater then <hi>Levi.)</hi> This the Apoſtle proves, becauſe he was greater then <hi>Abraham;</hi> in whoſe Joins <hi>Levi</hi> was: he proves him to be greater then <hi>Abraham,</hi> in that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> payed Tithes to him, and in that <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and without all contradiction the leſſe is bleſſed of the greater. (ſaith he) The Apoſtle having thus proved the perſon and prieſthood of Chriſt to be before and above that of <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> in the 11. verſe he ſhews, that the prieſthood of <hi>Levi</hi> was but imperfect in reſpect of Chriſts prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and therefore muſt juſtly now ceaſe, and be abrogated, when the prieſthood of Chriſt is come. According to that of the Apoſtle (in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 10. <hi>When that which is perfect is come, that which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect is done away:</hi> Now to prove that the prieſthood of <hi>Levi</hi> is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, he ſhews it, becauſe perfection, <hi>(viz:</hi> juſtification, ſanctification, and life eternall) could not be obtained by the Leviticall Prieſthood, <hi>viz:</hi> by their offering ſacrifices of buls, and goats, and rams, and lambes, &amp;c. for under their Prieſthood the people received that Law.) And he goes on to ſhew that this perfection was not to be found in that ſervice; for if it could have been found there, there had been no farther need that another Prieſt ſhould have riſen after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> which was a more excellent order then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of <hi>Levi.</hi> But ſeeing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prieſthood more excellent then that of <hi>Levi</hi> or <hi>Aaron, (viz:</hi> that of Chriſt) is riſen; in which there is perfection, <hi>viz:</hi> juſtification, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and eternall life to be found; (in the 12. verſe) he ſhews them that the Prieſthood is changed, and therefore that Law which they were tyed to under <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Levi (viz:</hi> of offering ſacrifices of buls
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117654:30"/> and goats, &amp;c.) is of neceſſity changed, and therefore muſt ceaſe to them: This Law (he ſaith) is changed, becauſe the Prieſthood is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged under which this Law was executed; and now another high Prieſt is riſen, <hi>(viz:</hi> Chriſt) who hath offered a ſacrifice once for ever.—So that by the Law here, the Apoſtle plainly means thoſe ſervices which (purſuing the ſame argument) he cals (in the next Chapter) the old Covenant, and a temporall Covenant, which was eſtabliſht and ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the legall prieſtood. And in this 12. verſe of this 7th Chapter, he ſhews the mutuall relation betwixt the Leviticall prieſthood and the old Covenant, that the Prieſthood ceaſing, when the prieſthood of Chriſt did riſe, the Law alſo, that old Covenant, muſt of neceſſity ceaſe, being eſtabliſht and ratified upon the Leviticall Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>Tis as much as if <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid, Your Prieſthood being imperfect, and abrogated by Chriſt, your law (by which you were bound by thoſe Prieſts to offer ſacrifices for ſin) doth now ceaſe too, Chriſt having once for all offered himſelf a ſacrifice for the ſins of his people.</p>
               <p>Now whether the words of the Apoſtle here, can by any (but ſuch as your ſelves) be wreſted to have any reference at all to Tithes, I leave all the world to judge. And I tell you, in your bold expounding the word <hi>[Law]</hi> here to be underſtood of Tithes, you have arrogated to your ſelves, more new and ſtrange light, then ever any man yet did, that undertook to expound this place of Scripture, ſince the Apoſtle did write it.—Oh glorious revelation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place, you ſay, there is not the leaſt ſyllable for it in the Goſpel, and the Apoſtles never owned it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Pray ſhew me where is the leaſt ſyllable againſt it in the Goſpel: or where did ever Chriſt or his Apoſtles diſown it? if your texts be no other againſt it then what you urge, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. 12. (though it may paſſe amongſt your ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and your ſilly women, who underſtand not Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) yet you will be laught and his't at, for your ſimplicitie, by thoſe who have any knowledge.—Shew me, I ſay, where the Law for pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tithes is abrogated in the new Teſtament: whether it be not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed (at leaſt in the equity of it) for Chriſt ſpeaking of tithing mint and cummin, ſaith. <hi>Theſe things ye ought to do, and not to leave the other undone. Luk.</hi> 11 42. You'le ſay, perhaps, that the prieſthood of the Law being ended, Tithes alſo, which was their due are ended in them This I know is your argument you truſt to.—But for Anſwer, I have ſhewed you already, that the paying of Tithes did not belong onely to the Leviticall Prieſthood; they were paid long before that Prieſthood was conſtituted.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:117654:30"/>
               <p> Again, in that <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> received Tithes from <hi>Abraham</hi> (which the Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. takes ſpeciall notice of foure or five times) ye may obſerve <hi>(Melchiſedech</hi> being a type of Chriſt) that Chriſt is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr. Reyn:</hi> Exp: Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 110.</note> of homage and tribute from his people. And farther, there was never any type of Chriſt, as a Prieſt, but he received Tithes as thoſe in the Law did: And theſe they received, not in the right of any thing in themſelves; but meerly in the virtue of their typicall office; ſo that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally they did manifeſtly pertain to that principall Prieſt whom theſe repreſented, whoſe perſonall Prieſthood is ſtanding for ever, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable and eternall; and therefore the rights, thereunto belonging are ſuch too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If it be objected by you, why then did not Chriſt in his life time receive Tithes.</p>
               <p>I anſwer. Firſt, becauſe though he were the ſubſtance, yet the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing typicall Prieſthood was not aboliſhed, till after his miniſtery on earth was finiſht; for his Prieſthood was not conſummate till his ſitting at the right hand of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he did not himſelf take Tithes, becauſe he took upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a voluntary poverty, for ſpeciall reaſons, belonging to the ſtate of his humiliation, and to the diſpenſation of mans redemption. See what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> You may (perchance) object farther, and ſay, now Chriſts prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is conſummate, and he himſelf is in heaven, whither no Tithes can be ſent; therefore none are due, becauſe he hath no typicall Prieſts on earth to repreſent him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Though Chriſt be in heaven in his body, yet he is on earth in his miniſtery; and in the diſpenſation of the virtue of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and the Miniſters of the Goſpel are in his ſtead: 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. and ought to be received as Chriſt himſelf: <hi>Galat.</hi> 4. 14. So that men are not by this excuſed from rendring Chriſts dues unto him; firſt, becauſe, there is in reſpect of him (whoſe ſacrifice we commemorate, and ſhew forth to the people) due, a teſtification of homage to him. 2ly, becauſe in reſpect of us there is due a reward of our labour;—for the labourer is worthy of his hire.</p>
               <p>Now to lay all theſe together in one view.—In as much as all the types of Chriſt (as Prieſts) have received Tithes as due; and in as much as that right was not grounded upon any thing in or from themſelves, but upon their typicall office, and ſo did originally pertain to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Prieſt whom they typified; And in as much as his perſon and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117654:31"/> office is eternall, and therefore ſuch are all the Annexa and dues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and in as much as he hath no where diſpenced with, denyed, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, or revoked this right, which from him (as the principall) all his types ever enjoyed. And laſtly, in as much as he hath left to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his Word the diſpenſation of his ſacrifice, and made them his Embaſſadors, and in his ſtead to the Church to ſet forth him crucified in his ordinances. For my part I deſire to be reſolved from you, (or by any other of your ſect, if there be any wiſer then other amongſt you) why unto them (in the name and right of their Maſter) thoſe rights ſhould not be due which were manifeſtly in his types, and of which he himſelf hath no where in his Word declared any revocation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you ſay, That receiving of Tithes is an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable hereſie, and a denying of Chriſt come in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Oh abominable ignorance! I ſee you had need to be told what hereſie is, (and I cannot yet but commend your deſire of being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to this point what hath been already ſpoken may ſatisfie reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men: And becauſe this is yet but <hi>(dictum)</hi> ſpoken by thoſe, who have ſpoken but little truth in this Paper, I muſt defer the giving any farther anſwer to it, till I receive ſome more of your new light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you will prove, that the receiving of Tithes, denyes Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, when I ſee how you go about to prove it; I doubt not but I ſhall ſhew your folly in that as in the reſt of your ſtuffe; therefore no more at preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your next objection againſt Tithes is this: (you ſay) if we were not wilfully blinde, we might ſee God blaſting them: for 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that ſcarce any of our poſterity come to any thing, but are generally miſerable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this I anſwer. Firſt, if you were acquainted with the Word of God, or any of his dealings with his people (as you pretend, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it appears to be but a pretence) you might know that proſperitie in this life, and increaſe in riches, is not alwayes a token of the favour of God. Read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 14. and there ye ſhall ſee who they are, whoſe portions are in this life, <hi>Whoſe bellies are fill'd, and who leave the reſt of their ſubſtance to their babes.</hi> For our parts, we are not envious at the fooliſh, when we ſee the proſperity of the wicked. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 3.</p>
               <p>Again, 2ly, that our poſterity are generally miſerable, is no better then a bold lye.</p>
               <p>3ly, If it were truth; yet the ſimplicitie of your argument appears to the world; I will make it appear to your ſelves: you argue thus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117654:31"/> men that receive Tithes do not grow rich, nor thrive in their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, therefore 'tis not lawfull to receive Tithes: You ſhall ſee the abſurditie of your concluſion, in turning it upon your ſelves, thus. Some men have been Mercers, and have broke in their Trade; ſome have been <note n="*" place="margin">Note that their new Paſtor hath paſt through all theſe Trades, &amp; Callings, and thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in none.</note> Stationers, Souldiers, Dairy-men, Schoolmaſters, &amp;c. and have been blaſted in all theſe, have not thrived in all or any of theſe, but in all have proved miſerable; therefore 'tis not lawfull for any man to be a Mercer, a Stationer, a Souldier, a Dairy-man, a Schoolmaſter, &amp;c. Do you ſee now what ſenſleſſe abſurd arguing this is?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place (you ſay) we call our ſelves the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> that we may have Tithes.<hi>—Anſ.</hi> This is another of your lyes.</p>
               <p>Again, in this we are Jewiſh.<hi>—Anſ.</hi> I have already manifeſted your ſimplicitie and ignorance in this; therefore 'tis worth no more words here: I paſſe it over.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Again you ſay, you plainly ſee upon what our Miniſtery ſtands; take away our honour and our means, and our gifts are taken away.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I have told you before whereupon our Miniſtery ſtands; and though you ſpeak ſo plainly, yet you have not (as yet) made it appear that our Miniſtery ſtands upon our honour and our means; but I doubt not but I ſhall make it appear to you, that both honour and means be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to our Miniſtery. In the mean time, let me know of you, when, or where did you ever know any mans gifts taken away with his means? either make it appear, or elſe ſit down, and acknowledge your ſelves to be men whoſe tongues are full of lying, ſlanders and reproaches. Doth this ſavour of the Spirit, ye pretend to be in you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Next you tell us, that we cannot live by Tent-making and preaching the Goſpel, by fiſhing and catching of men; how then ſhould we have time to tumble over the Fathers? But <hi>Paul</hi> wanted for back and belly, yet was not wanting in preaching the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer: (though we cannot) yet ſome in theſe late dayes have learn'd ſo to fiſh, and to catch men, that they can live by it, when (the world knows) they could never live, by continuing in that honeſt calling, unto which God had called them; they learn to forget that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 20. where he commands, <hi>Let every man abide in the ſame calling wherein he was called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, for our tumbling over the Fathers; you that ſpeak ſo ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully of thoſe worthy men, (whoſe pions labours and memories are precious with all godly and underſtanding men) you, I ſay, might
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:117654:32"/> very well imploy your time in going to ſchoo! to them a while (if you were able to underſtand them) by whom you might be convinced of the wickedneſſe of thoſe wayes you are now ſeduced to walk in; and that ye might be taught how to underſtand the Word, which now you ſo ſhamefully abuſe: and that you might be directed by them to walk in that truth which you are now ſo ignorant of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> The next nayl you drive at in a great deal of your ſtuffe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is to tell us how we ought to preach the Goſpel, and to labour with our own hands, as <hi>Peter</hi> by fiſhing, and <hi>Paul</hi> by Tent-making.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. I doubt not, but that <hi>Paul</hi> whom you have inſtanced in for preaching the Goſpel, and working with his own hands, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to you, your malice and your folly, and your ſyllineſſe in object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this to us: <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf will teach you (if you do not look upon this part of his doctrine as <hi>Apocrypha)</hi> firſt, that liberall maintenance is due to us from the people for our preaching the Goſpel: and 2ly, that this is due not out of mercy (as if our maintenance ought to depend on the voluntary contributions of our Pariſhioners) but out of juſtice for our works ſake, as we labour in the Word and doctrine.—And farther, that they who do labour in the Word and doctrine, have power to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from labouring with their own hands, it is not required of them that they ſhould live by fiſhing or Tent-making, but 'tis allowed them that they ſhould live by the Goſpel.—For the proof of theſe things, ſee firſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate to him that teacheth, in all his goods.</hi> (ſo the word is in the originall) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17, 18. <hi>The Elders that labour in the Word and doctrine are worthy of double honour. For the Scripture ſaith, Thouſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the ex that treadeth out the corn, for the labourer is worthy of his reward.</hi> But if you will look into 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 3. and ſo forward in the Chapter, ye ſhall there ſee <hi>Paul</hi> ſtating and debating the queſtion at large, <hi>Who goes to warfare at any time at his own charges? who plants a vineyard, and eats not of the fruit thereof? or who feeds a flock, and eats not of the milk of the flock? Say I theſe things as a man?</hi> that is, Am I partiall? do I ſpeak meerly out of affection, and humane favour to my own cauſe or calling? <hi>or ſaith not the Law the ſame alſo? For it is written in the Law of Moſes, Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the ox that treadeth out the corn: doth God take care for oxen? Or ſaith he it altogether for our ſakes?</hi> that is, Doth God provide Laws for the rewarding and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging the labour of bruit beaſts; and doth he leave the maintenance and honour of his own immediate officers to the arbitrary and pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allowances of covetous and cruell men? <hi>For our ſakes (no doubt) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:117654:32"/> 
                  <hi>this written: that he that plougheth, ſhould plough in hope: and he that threſheth in hope, ſhould be partaker of his hope.</hi> That is, that the incouragement of the Miniſters in their ſervice might depend upon ſuch a hope as is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Gods Law and proviſion; And that they might not be left to the will and allowances of thoſe men againſt whoſe ſins they were ſent. And this the Apoſtle proves farther, by an argument drawn from a moſt unanſwerable, equitie.<hi>—If we have ſown unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing, if we ſhall reap your carnall things?</hi> Again, <hi>Do ye not know, that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? and they which wait at the Altar, are partakers of the Altar?</hi> (to ſhew that they receive their maintenance from the hand of God himſelf, whoſe onely the things of the Altar are) <hi>Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> He ſaith not, that God permitteth or alloweth, but God ordaineth and commandeth it. And pray tell me, what is it to live? firſt, they muſt live as men; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey muſt have enough for neceſſitie. 2ly, they muſt live as beleevers; <hi>He that provideth not for his own, is worſe then an Infidel:</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8. They muſt therefore have of the Goſpel, ſufficient to lay up for thoſe whom the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w of common huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (much more of faith) commands them to provide for. 3ly, they muſt live as Miniſters, they muſt have wherewith to maintain the duties of their calling, a good example of pietie, charitie, and hoſpitalitie. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 3. 2. &amp; 4 Ch: 12. v. From this you may obſerve, that thoſe who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the Word and Doctrine, and are Embaſſadors for Chriſt, and ſtand in his ſtead, to reveal his myſteries, and diſpence the treaſures of his blood in the Church, ought to have, (by way of homage to Chriſt, and by way of recompence and retribution to themſelves) a liberall maintenance, and fitting the honour and dignity of that perſon whom they repreſent, and of that ſervice wherein they miniſter. The Apoſtle ſaith, they <hi>are worthy of double honour;</hi> honour of reverence, and honour of maintenance.</p>
               <p>Again, farther yet: to ſhew you that this maintenance ought not to depend upon the voluntary contribution of the people, as an act of Mercie, and not of Juſtice. The ſame <hi>Paul</hi> tels the ſame <hi>Corinthians</hi> in the ſame Chapter, that he and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did not work with their hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not power to demand and receive maintenance from them for their preaching the Goſpel to them: <hi>Am I not an Apoſtle?</hi> (ſaith he) what then? <hi>Have we not power to eat and to drink? Have we not power to leade about a wiſe, a ſiſter, as well as the other Apoſtles, and as the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas? Or I onely and Barnabas? Have not we power to forbear work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:117654:33"/> The Apoſtle plainly intimates in theſe 4, 5, and 6 verſes, that all the other Apoſtles did receive maintenance from the people for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their wives, and that they had power ſo to do, as they were Apoſtles. And pray tell me, whom do you finde of the Apoſtles (beſides <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas)</hi> who (after they did preach the Goſpel) did ever work with their hands (for their living) in their former Trades and Callings? but had maintenance by the preaching of the Goſpel, and had power to receive it. And <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf tels them there (as you have ſeen) that he and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> did not work for this, that they had no power to receive maintenance by the Goſpel as well as the other Apoſtles, and power to leave working with their hands, but they did it for other ends.</p>
               <p>Hence now (as you ſay, if you be not quite blinde) ye may ſee, that liberall maintenance is due to the Miniſters of the Goſpel, as Miniſters for their works ſake; That they have power to take this from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and power to leave working with their own hands for their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.—Let me hear what you have to ſay to theſe things.</p>
               <p>Again, ſee 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 15. <hi>Meditate on theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them; that thy profiting may be known to all.</hi> Anſwer me; what doth <hi>Paul</hi> mean, by bidding <hi>Timothy</hi> to give himſelf <hi>wholly</hi> to theſe things? had it not ſounded like a contradiction if it had run thus; Labour with thy own hands at ſome trade for thy living, and give thy ſelf wholly to reading, exhortation, doctrine, meditation? do you ſee your ſimplicity and ignorance now in this malicious objection againſt us?</p>
               <p>Farther yet. I hope by this reaſonable men may be convinc'd, that it is a divine right that Miniſters ſhould have a maintenance, and that for their preaching the Goſpel: And for the proportion, diſtribution, the manner of the peoples paying, and their receiving that mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, their uſe and enjoyment of it, if you look upon it, and we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be of a civill right; Then if by the Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the proportion of Tithes be allowed us, and we by the ſame Laws hold and poſſeſſe them (there being nothing in the whole written Word to forbid ſuch a way, and ſuch a proportion) it appears to rationall men, that we have as lawfull a Freehold in our Tithes, as any man, hath to his Lands, and can enjoy and poſſeſſe them, without being guilty of abominable hereſie; and without a denying of Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Again, as for our receiving, ſo for your paying Tithes; know this, that it being the Apoſtles doctrine, that Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117654:33"/> live by the Goſpel; And the Miniſters of this Kingdom being allowed and authorized, by the juſt Laws and lawfull Magiſtrates of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to receive Tithes of their people; and every man being compell'd under the penalty of the Law of this Kingdom, to the payment of them (there being nothing, no not a word) in the Word of God to forbid ſuch a law, I ſay, Tithes becoming this way due to us by the Law of the Land, and the Apoſtle commanding all Chriſtians <hi>(Rom.</hi> 13. 7.) to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to all their dues; whoſoever ſhall go about to defraud, or to deny their Miniſter this his due, he is in this moſt impious, and ſacrilegious.</p>
               <p>Will you be aſhamed now of your ignorance? and be a little more wary for the time to come, how you give liberty to your unbridled tongues, and diſtempered paſſions to cenſure, miſreport, or ſlander, or ſcandalize the perſons, parts, callings, maintenance of ſuch men againſt whom <hi>Timothy</hi> was not to receive an accuſution without two or three witneſſes: 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 19.—and to take notice of the ill conſequences of the ſame; you do not onely contract the guilt of ſin to your ſelves; but you expoſe your ſelves in your madneſſe, ignorance, malice and folly, to be the object of ſorrow and grief to thoſe that know you, and pitie your poore ſouls; and the object of laughter to all others, that have any knowledge of the truth.</p>
               <p>In your next paſſage you expreſſe more of that bitterneſſe that is in your ſpirits: (poore men) There be ſome <hi>Symons</hi> crept in amongſt you, which (as he did in <hi>Act.</hi> 8.) do bewitch you, who ſeems to you to be ſome great one; and (as the people beleeved of him) ſo do many now give heed to many that be abroad, as if they were the great power of God; whereas (indeed) in the end they will prove to be but ſorcerers. And as for all your wicked and falſe accuſations, I ſhall onely ſay to you (as <hi>Peter</hi> did to <hi>Simon) Repent of this your wickedneſſe, and pray God, if perhaps the thoughts of your hearts may be forgiven you.</hi> For 'tis eaſie for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to perceive, that theſe are the expreſſions of thoſe who are in the very gaul of bitterneſſe, and bond of iniquity. Look upon ſome of them, and you your ſelves ſhall be Judges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> You ſay peremptorily that we ſtrike at the very foundation of Truth, as he that is ſpirituall may eaſily diſcern, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, I will not undertake to judge your ſpirits; but this I muſt tell you, that (how ſpirituall ſoever you pretend to be) that ſpirit that charges us with ſtriking at the very foundation of Truth, is a ſpirit of envie, hatred, malice, reviling, evill ſpeaking, lying and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering; and what ſpirit this is, I leave it to your ſelves to judge.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:117654:34"/>
               <p> 2ly, Me thinks you ſhould not ſo cruelly have condemned us for this, but you ſhould have told us what truth we did ever ſtrike at; you have quickly forgotten your own rule, but now given to us, concerning he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and hereticks: you told us that the Goſpel way, was firſt to prove men ſuch, and then to reprove; but it ſeems you walk not in the ſame Goſpel way. Remember here that of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 2. 1, 3. <hi>Thou art inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt: for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou condemneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doeſt the ſame things. And thinkeſt thou this, that judgeſt another, and doeſt the ſame things, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgement of God?</hi> you ſhould firſt prove us ſuch, and then condemne us. 'Tis your own counſell, and therefore (I hope) will not be rejected by you. I deſire that this may be proved againſt us, elſe ſurely 'twill condemne you.</p>
               <p>3ly. I doubt not, but in the end, and upon the tryall it ſhall be made appeare that in thoſe very things (wherein you raſhly condemne us, for ſtriking at the foundation of truth) the Lord himſelfe (whoſe eyes are upon the truth) and all that are acquainted with any of the truths of God, will acquit and juſtifie us, as contending only for the truth that was once delivered to the Saints, and ſtriving for the faith of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, which is now invaded and miſerably wounded by thoſe ſpirits that are already, whom (as the Apoſtle fore-told) the way of truth is evill ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place, you charge us with deceiving the hearts of the ſimple, and endeavouring to deceive the very elect, that we make truth looke every way (like <hi>Janus</hi> faces) that you have need of the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God to diſcover us, and the depths of Satans deceipts and wiles, that the Lord, who hath begun to uncover, unvayl, unmask, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath, &amp;c. will do it fully, and will tread Satan under foot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, in that wee are charged as deceivers. I tell you here againe we can (we bleſſe God) ſpeake it before God, that we are not as many, that deale deceitfull with the word of God, but as of ſincerity, as of God, in the ſight of God ſpeake we in Chriſt, and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>We ſhall endeavour</hi> (under all your reproaches) <hi>to approve our ſelves as the Miniſters of God in much patience, by honour and diſhonour, by evill report and good report, as deceivers and yet true.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2ly. We cannot but ſmile at your compariſon: Can you <hi>Tho. Clut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbuck,</hi> or you <hi>Tho. Sheppard,</hi> or the Ironmonger, or Shoomaker, or Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice-maker, or any of you tell what <hi>Janus</hi> faces meane?—Poore men (though you ſeeme to ſcorne the pretious fountaines as you call them)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117654:34"/> yet it ſeems you do ſometimes ſo farre forget your ſelves, as to make uſe of heathen hiſtories.</p>
               <p>3ly, The Lord give you his wiſdome, (if it be his will) that you may be once able to diſcerne the depths of Satans deceipts and wiles: And let the Lord go on (in much mercy to your ſoules) to pluck off Satans maske and vizard, to uncloath, unvaile and uncover to you, the hidden things of darkneſſe, which are at preſent ſo imbraced by you as new light: 'Tis the deſire of our ſoules (the Lord knowes) to have Satan diſcovered and trodden under foot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you ſay, though you have been as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe to carry the falſe Prophets and to call them Divines, yet God having now opened your eyes, you dare not goe forward in that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, if ever in your lives, you carried the burthen of <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> Aſſe, you doe now: we have given you ſome deſcriptions already out of theſe two Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude,</hi> wherein as in a glaſſe (I told you) you might ſee the faces of thoſe whom yee follow. And both thoſe Apoſtles doe likewiſe add this of them: they have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray following the way of <hi>Balaam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Boſor</hi> who loved the wayes of unrighteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15. Againe, <hi>Woe unto them, for they have gone in the way of</hi> Caine, <hi>and runne greedily after the error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for reward,</hi> Epiſtle of <hi>Jude</hi> ver. 11. And if your eyes were were but ſo farre open'd, (if you were not more blind then <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe was) yee might ſee the Angel with his drawne Sword in his hand ready to deſtroy you for your running on thus to curſe the people of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Next, you ſay, that we run you through with the Sword of reproach, and had wee the Sword of the Magiſtrate in our hands we would have ſlaine you, becauſe you would not obey us rather then God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> All that I ſay to this, is, as formerly I have ſpoken to ſome of the like ſtuffe, the Lord rebuke thee, thou falſe tongue, the righteous God judge betwixt you and us in theſe things, which of us, or in what have any of us, at any time deſired you to obey any of us rather then God? Set us know, or elſe recant and repent: however this is our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that the Lord will cleare this one day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your next part you cry out of the monſtrous deſperate he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks of theſe times, that condemne your gentle, meeke, curteous car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, your civility, and your moderate brotherly walking for ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of hereſie.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:117654:35"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I beleeve this comes, from a marke of a falſe Prophet, which was lately given you amongſt other notes, by which you were directed to know them, this was given to you as one, <hi>viz</hi> a counterfeit humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and this is no other marke then what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe gives of falſe Prophets, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 18, 23. therefore ſure this is no ſuch abominable monſtrous and deſperate hereſie, as you call it. And for your parts whether your meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, courteouſneſſe, civility, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, walking as brethren (which you pretend ſo much to) be in you in truth, or whether it be counterfeit, I leave it to God (who ſees the inſide) to judge, and to the world, to whoſe eyes this Paper of yours may come; ye have here indeed given us a Taſt of your meekneſſe, of your civility, gentleneſſe, moderation, and of the Saint-like, Lamb-like ſpirit that is in you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your next place, you tell us, that we owne in words Chriſt to be our Lord and Maſter, and call our ſelves his Miniſters, if you are ſo, then (ſay you) we hope you are able to produce his commiſſion for what you doe. And if Chriſt be your only Lord and Law-giver how comes it to paſſe, that you winde and turne at every command of men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, wee doe owne Chriſt to be our Lord and Maſter, and Chriſt hath, and we doubt not but he ever will owne us to be his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; ſo long as wee are able to produce his commiſſion for what we do. That we have his commiſſion for our office and miniſtery, that I have ſhewed you before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> But (ſay you) if Chriſt be your onely Lord and Law-giver, how comes it to paſſe that you turne and wind at every command of men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, we acknowledge Chriſt to be our only Lord and Law-giver. But we deſire (for the information of your ignorance) to let you know, that Chriſt gives Laws either immediately, or mediatly. The immediate laws of Chriſt are thoſe which are ſet downe in his written Word. But 2ly, he gives laws mediately, by thoſe lawfull Magiſtrates, who are Gods ordinance amongſt men. Now when the commands of lawfull Magiſtrates (whom you call men, and God cals Gods) are ſuch as are no way contrary to, or diſagreeing from, but agreeable to the written word of Chriſt, (in a word) when their commands are onely in things lavvfull, honeſt, juſt, and good; our obeying them (vvhich you call vvinding and turning) is no leſſe then an obeying of Chriſt our Lord and Lavv-giver, vvho by his Apoſtles hath commanded us, to be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117654:35"/> ſubject to the higher povvers, for the povvers that be, are ordained of God, and hath told us likevviſe that vvhoſoever reſiſteth, reſiſts the ordinance of God, and they ſhall receive to themſelves damnation, for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for thy good. Wherefore vve muſt needs be ſubject not only for vvrath but for conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3, 4. <hi>&amp;c.—</hi>And againe, <hi>ſubmit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be unto the King as ſupreame, or unto Governours, as unto thoſe that are ſent by him,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 14.—Novv on the other ſide, I deſire you to make it good to me (if you can) vvhere any of us have turned and winded at any other commands of men, then ſuch as have been the lawfull commands of lawfull Magiſtrates, whom (I ſay) we are commanded to obey, for the Lords ſake, and for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place. If Chriſt be your Lord (ſay you) where is his command that you ſhould go ſeven yeers or more to the Univerſity to fit your ſelves; and then, and not before to preach: and that unleſſe you do, you muſt not preach.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Oh ridiculous ſimplicitie and ſyllineſſe! may I not as well ask you <hi>Thomas</hi> the Clothier, <hi>Giles</hi> the Mercer, <hi>Roger</hi> the Shoomaker, <hi>Samuel</hi> the Boddice-maker, and <hi>William</hi> the Ironmonger, you profeſſe that Chriſt is your Lord and Maſter; where's his command that you ſhould ſerve ſeven yeers under a Maſter at your Trade, and that then you ſhould ſet up your trade for your ſelves, and not before? I will anſwer your <hi>quaere</hi> in ſuch a compariſon. Thus,—you know that it is God's will that every man have ſome or other lawfull Calling to abide in, and to labour. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 20. 22. 24. Now the Common-wealth in which you live, hath in Chriſtian policy, thought it good to Enact ſuch a Law, that none ſhall have leave, to ſet up any Trade in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, till they have ſerved ſuch a time in the Trade; And this is grounded upon ſeverall reaſons. As firſt to avoid confuſion in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: 2ly, that men might be thereby enabled and fitted for their callings; leſt entring upon them without knowledge, they (firſt) abuſe and undo their ſelves for want of skill: and 2ly, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth be not abuſed, by their venting and ſelling Wares not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, and uſefull, and the like. To clear this to you in an inſtance, if every man, that had a will to it, ſhould freely ſet up the Trade of a Mercer, Shoo-maker, Boddice-maker, Ironmonger, Clothier, &amp;c. who had not ſerved at the Trade, and had no knowledge in the Trade, you would preſently judge, that here were like to be a fair Trade, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth was like to be well ſerved, and we ſhould have ſtrange
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117654:36"/> commodities from them, poore Cloth, Shooes, Boddice, &amp;c.—This by way of compariſon.</p>
               <p>And from this to ſhew you in like manner, that the office of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel of Chriſt, and adminiſtring of Sacraments, is a diſtinct office in the Church: It is the will and command of Chriſt that ſuch as undertake, and enter into this office, ſhould be qualified with abilities, parts, and gifts, fitting for ſo great a work, he muſt not be <hi>a novice,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 6. he <hi>muſt be able to teach others:</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. he muſt be <hi>a workman, ſo able to divide the Word of God aright, as that he need not to be aſhamed:</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15. Where this ability is wanting, the Church of Chriſt is like to be as ill ſerved, as the Common-wealth by ſimple and unskilfull Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.—Now the Apoſtle tels us, that the Scriptures <hi>are ſufficient to make the man of God perfect, and to furniſh him throughly to all good works:</hi> (that is) to all the ſervices of his profeſſion, to thoſe works of his calling he mentioned before, <hi>viz: doctrine, reproof, correction, and inſtruction:</hi> for theſe things the Scriptures are ſufficient to furniſh a man: But now for the ſufficient underſtanding, and not perverting, and wreſting of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, learning is requiſite and neceſſary. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. latter end.</p>
               <p>To clear this farther to you, you muſt know, that there be two great works which belong to this high calling: firſt Inſtruction of the ſcholar: 2ly, conviction of the adverſaries. Now every underſtanding man can judge how many different parts of learning are requiſite to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> Exp: Pſal. 110. pa. 268.</note> of theſe two ſervices. Firſt, there muſt be knowledge in the tongues, for the better underſtanding of the holy Scriptures, by their originall Idiom and emphaſis; for in Tranſlations there may be, and are ſome errors; for though the Scriptures be the infallible Word of God, yet the Tranſlators are men, which are ſubject to errour, and may miſtake. 2ly, There is required the knowledge of the Arts to obſerve the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nnexion, the argumentation, and method of them. 3ly, there is required knowledge of ancient cuſtomes, Hiſtory, and Antiquitie, of the <hi>Babylonians, Perſians, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Romanes:</hi> without in-ſight whereinto, the full meaning of many paſſages of holy Scripture cannot be clearly underſtood and apprehended. 4ly, there is required School-learning, for the diſcovering and repelling of the ſubtilty of the adverſaries (and becauſe <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate ſaw that the Chriſtians in his time made excellent uſe of this, in repelling and beating down his errors, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore interdicted them, the uſe of Schools of Learning; whoſe examples many Apoſtates from our Church follow in theſe dayes, who cry out againſt all humane Learning as the weapons of Gentiles, and not fit for Chriſtians to uſe.)</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:117654:36"/>
               <p> Laſtly, there is required a knowledge of the Hiſtories and Antiquities of the Church, that we may obſerve the ſucceſſion of the Profeſſors and doctrines thereof, the originals ſprouting of Hereſie therein, and the better to anſwer the reproaches of our inſolent adverſaries, who lay innovation to our charge.</p>
               <p>In a word, men cannot underſtand the Scripture in their originall languages without the tongues, they cannot expound without Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, nor perſwade without Rhetoricke, nor divide without Logick, nor ſound the depth of any controverſie, without Philoſophy and ſchool divinity. Now ſeeing all this learning is requiſite, for the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, expounding, dividing the word aright, and for inſtructiing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting and perſwading thereby, and for the convincing the gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof. You muſt know, that there are but two waies (that ever we heard of) for the gaining of theſe requiſites. The firſt is extraordinary, the immediate inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt, and the miraculous gifts of Tongues and Prophecy. And 2ly, The ordinary acquiring of theſe by the means which God hath vouchſafed <hi>viz.</hi> Schools of learning, and our applying our ſelves to, and our endeavours in them.—The firſt of theſe waies, <hi>viz.</hi> the gaining of theſe abilities, by immediate inſpiration and revolation, hath ceaſed in the Church of Chriſt theſe many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, even ever ſince the time of the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who (being in themſelves ſome of them (before their calling to their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip) unlearned men) did receive their gifts and abilities this way: <hi>Acts</hi> 2. And many other Primitive Chriſtians with them in thoſe daies: but thoſe Irradiations, Revelations and Inſpirations of the Spirit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the fiery Tongues have ceaſed for many hundred yeares, and have not been ſeen in any Chriſtian Church of late. Therefore there remains onely that other ordinary way of gaining theſe abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which I have mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> in the lawfull and diligent uſe of the means; by going to the Univerſity (as you call it) or to ſome Schooles where learning is to be had, to fit our ſelves.—</p>
               <p>Now then—ſeeing the office of the Miniſtery is a diſtinct office, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that enter into it muſt be furniſht with abilities, gifts, and partes enabling them to teach, and by the word to inſtruct, to correct, to exhort and to convince, ſeeing theſe parts and abilities, are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired miraculoully, but acquired in and by the uſe of means, ſeeing theſe means are the Schools of Learning; ſeeing through the uſe of theſe means (by Gods bleſſing on our endeavours) we attain to theſe abilities and parts; And ſeeing the Spirit of God directs and enables us
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117654:37"/> by theſe abilities and parts, to divide the word aright, to inſtruct, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, correct, and convince &amp;c. I hope that the ſimplicity of your <hi>Quaere,</hi> and the the ſufficiency of our commiſſion in this, doth viſibly appear to rationall men.</p>
               <p>And before I leave this point, let me tell you, that we can never ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admire nor deteſt, the ſaucineſſe of thoſe bold Intruders in theſe dayes, who venture to become teachers of the ignorant before them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have been Diſciples of the Learned; who being rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned (I had almoſt ſaid illiterate) mechanicks without calling, and without knowledge, do ſo boldly and preſumptuouſly leap from their manuall Trades into this ſacred and dreadfull office, of which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf could cry out, who is ſufficient? And though ſome of them pretend to a calling to it, and to gifts and abilities; for their calling I would feigne know who is the author of it: if they avouch God; I would require that they ſhould prove th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their calling from God by ſome evident ſigne: for whenſoever it pleaſeth God to change the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe, and to cal any man to any office extraordinary, he declares that his good will and pleaſure by ſome evident ſigne. Now if the calling of our <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> new teachers, be ordinary, let them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it by the Scripture, if extraordinary, let them prove it by ſigne and by miracl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. And as for their gifts and abilities (in which they ſay they are ſpirituall men, and have all the gifts from the ſpirit: I ſhall tell you that (whatſoever their pretences be to the Spirit and Revelations and Infuſions) yet ſeeing they cannot do as thoſe Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians did; ſeeing they come as far ſhort of thoſe Chriſtians in extraordinary gifts, as they do behind them in time; ſeeing they are ſo far from ſpeaking with ſtrange Tongues, that they cannot ſpeake cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly</hi> Dipper dipt.</note> and coherently in their own mother-Tongue; ſeeing they are many times ſo wide from the ſence of ſome Scriptures they venture to expound and apply, that their Expoſitions and Applications are oft without ſence; ſeeing they utter old broken Notes taken from other mens Sermons, for new Revelations; ſeeing they furbiſh up ancient he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies that have layen long in the dark, for Chriſtian Armour of light; ſeeing in their Interpretations they not onely contradict Scripture, but themſelves; ſeeing their prophecyings are but vain janglings; (though ſome of them have got a glib tongue, and thereby ſlide into the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the vulgar ſort) ſeeing in their contemplations they oft ſoar ſo high, as that they looſe themſelves; and vent blaſphemies and groſſe errors, for viſions and revelations of the Spirit. Seeing (I ſay) that (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117654:37"/> all their ſpecious pretences) theſe be their fruits, as the very ſad experience of theſe times, do too well manifeſt to the world; They ſhall give us leave to eſteeme them no Prophets, but Enthuſiaſts; no inſpired men, but diſtracted; no Seers, but dreamers; no Expoſitors, but Impoſtors; no workmen, but botchers; no fixed ſtars, but wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; no lights, but exhalations incenſed in the night, which leade fools out of their way, ſometimes into thickets, ſometimes into ditches and quagmyres, and many into Rivers over head and ears.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your next <hi>Quaere</hi> is, where is our command that we ſhould admit any to either ſeals, before they can make it viſibly to appeare that they are in Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here you begin to ſpeak a little plainly, and to tell us now what Religion you are of, <hi>viz.</hi> pure <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> I know your meaning is, where is our commiſſion to baptize Infants? for theſe cannot make it viſibly appeare that they are in Chriſt: I anſwer, where is your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Chriſt, to require all thoſe that would be admitted to the ſeals, firſt to make it viſibly appear, that they have intereſt in Chriſt? I here undertake to make it good to you from the Word of God; firſt that it is an unwarrantable practice, in you or any other, and an unjuſt ſcrupuloſity to require ſatisfaction of the true grace, and reall holines of every one that is admitted a member of the viſible Church: what do you think of the Apoſtles baptizing <hi>Simon Magus, Act.</hi> 8. 13. 'tis true, the text ſaith, that <hi>he beleeved alſo, and was baptized:</hi> but all the world knows, and acknowledges that that beleeving, was but an externall profeſſion of faith (being convinced by miracles of Gods power) did he, or could he make it (viſibly) appear, that he had intereſt in Chriſt? The Apoſtles tell him afterward in that Chapter, that he was <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe, and the bond of iniquitie;</hi> yet having before made but an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion of faith in Chriſt, he was admitted to baptiſme. And where there is ſuch an outward profeſſion made, you cannot anſwer the denying the ſeal of Baptiſme to ſuch a one; And we have no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to require a farther ſatisfaction of their reall intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And therefore 2ly, I likewiſe undertake to make it good to, &amp; againſt you, and your <hi>Goliah</hi> (who ever he be) that children of beleeving, and Chriſtian parents ought to be admitted to the firſt ſeal of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>viz:</hi> Baptiſme: and if you require a ſyllabicall command for this practiſe; I deſire to know of you on the contrary, where Chriſt or his Apoſtles have in plain tearms forbidden, or denyed them this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, or where we are commanded not to admit them? becauſe the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:117654:38"/> Church wherein we live, hath been for many hundred yeers, and is ſtill to this day, in poſſeſſion and practice of this ordinance; I (being alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſatisfied in my own conſcience) muſt hear from you, what you have to ſay againſt this practice, before I ſpend more labour in the defence of it: if you have any thing, to ſay againſt it, let me hear what it is; and I doubt not, but I ſhall eaſily make it appear to you, that your denying the Sacrament of Baptiſme to Infants of Parents profeſſing faith, is an hereticall opinion and practice; and ſo convince you of your errour herein; And I ſhall likewiſe in that ſhew you our commiſſion from Chriſt for this practice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place, you ask us, where is our command to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit prophane drunkards, ſwearers, lyars, or raylers, to the Lords table?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, whoſoever charges us with admitting prophane drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, ſwearers, lyars, or raylers (as ſuch) to the Lords Supper, they are lyars, and raylers. 2ly, I demand of you whether if a man hath once been a drunkard, lyar, ſwearer, &amp;c. he may never be admitted, becauſe he hath been formerly ſuch a one? or whether thoſe that have been ſuch, may not be admitted when they give viſible teſtimonies and profeſſions of their repentance, of their deſires to wait upon God in that ordinance, for their receiving a ſeal of the pardon of their former ſins upon their repentance and faith in Chriſt; and for increaſing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and ſtrengthening that grace they have already received in their converſion? If becauſe ſome men have been ſuch, they therefore may never be admitted, upon any tearms, if that be your opinion, the Lord deliver me from it: if you would deal truly with your own ſouls, and look in upon your ſelves, may it not be ſaid to you, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to his <hi>Corinthians:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Such were ſome of you:</hi> And I heartily wiſh that you did not give ſuch occaſion (as many of you do) to the world ſtill to ſay, ſuch are ſome of you: I do not know what your Communion is, or what your ordinances be which you follow, and communicate in ſince you renounced our Church; but (for all your out-cryes againſt our prophane mixtures and communions; I beleeve if God would give you hearts to ſearch, and ſee among your ſelves, you would quickly finde, that you are not all of you ſuch Saints, as you would fain paſſe for. The ſhamefull corruptions which might be found amongſt your ſelves, would ſtop your mouthes from crying out againſt confuſed and mixt communion with the prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Your next <hi>Quaere</hi> is, where hath Chriſt commanded, that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Miniſters ſhould take Tythes?</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:117654:38"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ask you, pray tell me, where hath Chriſt forbidden either them to take, or the people to pay Tithes?</p>
               <p>Again (me thinks) (men that can take that liberty that you can) ſhould not be ſo hard driven for accuſations againſt us, as to be fain to repeat the ſame thing twice or thrice over; which you had ſo largely urged before: I have ſaid enough already to ſatisfie this ſilly queſtion; and therefore ſhall meddle no more with theſe Coleworts twice or thrice ſod.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Laſtly, you ask me, where's our command that after perſons are admitted Church-members, (by which they have a right to all the priviledges thereof) that we muſt examine them, whether they be fit or no; or to deny any, if they refuſe to be examined by us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> How do you contradict your ſelves in theſe your <hi>Quaeries,</hi> which are within half a ſcore lines: before you askt us, what command we had, to admit prophane ones, who were unfit? here you ask us what authority we have to examine them, concerning their fitneſſe, or unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before we admit them? you tell us 'tis unwarrantable practice to keep any away who are members; and the ground upon which you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this to be unwarrantable practice, is, becauſe they are members, and ſo have right to all the priviledges of the Church. Here let me ask you, whether or no thoſe who are admitted members of the viſible Church, if after their admiſſion they fall into prophaneneſſe, into groſs and ſcandalous ſins (as their being Church-members doth not put them into an impoſſibilitie of committing ſome ſuch ſins) if (I ſay) after they are members, they fall into ſuch practiſes; muſt they be admitted to all priviledges, and communion in all ordinances meerly upon this ground becauſe they are already members? and muſt no lawfull means be uſed to bring them to a ſight thereof, and to repentance, and to fit them far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ordinances, becauſe they are already members? what ſimple wilde fellow is't that leads you into theſe ſtrange conceits? what think you of the inceſtuous perſon, in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. was he not a member? did he not commit a grievous ſin? might not he (upon your argument have pleaded a right to all priviledges, as he was a member? yet for all this the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had a command to caſt him out. Now for our caſting out (you ſay) if any of our members be unfit (as queſtionleſſe there may be an unfitneſſe in ſome members, in any Church) why is he not caſt out? (ſay you) what will no leſſe puniſhment ſerve turn? nothing but caſt him out preſently? we would fain know of you, where is your, or any Churches authority, to caſt out a member,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117654:39"/> for every ſin that may make him unfit at preſent for communicating, in the Lords Supper? or is the caſting him out of the Church the onely way to make him fit? whether or no is it not (even in your weak judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) a more likely way, in a milde and brotherly manner, firſt in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate to admoniſh, to reprove, to convince, to exhort, to inſtruct, to the end ſuch a one may be fit, and if no other means will ſerve, then to caſt out.</p>
               <p>But for our caſting out, I have told you already, that the power of our Church in the execution of ſuch things, is taken away by thoſe, who will have Liberty to be, and to doe any thing, and yet not be caſt out. Surely therefore your charging us with theſe things and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us for confuſion, is an uncharitable and an unwarrantable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In your next particular you tell us, that whereas we ſay that hereticks ſpread errors and hereſies without oppoſition; furely we muſt meane our ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Truly, 'tis very wittily concluded; we deſire you to proove this, that we are hereticks, that we acknowledge our ſelves to be ſuch; that our doctrine is pernicious and falſe (for this you charge us with) prove this (I ſay) againſt us, or elſe you will be poſted for the muſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent malicious lyars, revilers and ſlanderers, that this generation hath brought forth.—For any thing elſe that is in this particular of your Paper, 'tis anſwered before, and therefore not worthy of any more time here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next particular there are two things to be ſpoken to. Firſt you tell me that whereas I ſay I love true grace, piety and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſhall be willing to embrace it though it come from the breaſt of the greateſt enemy (here's a myſtery wants unfolding, and (in the cloſe of this particular) you tell me wherein the myſtery lyes) you ſay, my expreſſion hints to you, that true grace, piety, and holineſſe, and I are enemies: for can it be, that if you have true grace (ſay you) that another that hath true grace, and you ſhould be enemies, yea the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt enemies, when true grace makes of the greateſt enemies, the neereſt and ſtrongeſt friends: ſure (ſay you) you did not conſider what you writ, or if you did, you ſhould have done well to have explained your meaning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer. Firſt, I did very well conſider what I writ, when I ſaid that I loved true grace, piety and holyneſſe, and ſhould be willing to embrace it, though it come from the boſome of the greateſt enemy:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117654:39"/> And he that is but one ace, or one inch above a novice, is able to tell you that this is no myſtery, and needs no unfolding; but it being my misfortune to deale with thoſe whoſe foggy ignorance makes them thinke, every plaine truth to be a myſtery, I muſt and will explaine my meaning to you in a few words: You ſay that my expreſſion hints that true grace, piety, and holineſſe, and I are enemies. I anſwer, 'tis not my expreſſion but the Devils, the Father of lyes that hinted (that) to you from that expreſſion.</p>
               <p>I love true grace, piety and holineſſe, though it come from the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemy: How doth this expreſſion hint to you that true grace, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and holyneſſe and I are enemies? how ridiculous is your malice and ignorance? can it be (ſay you) that if you have true grace, another that hath true grace and you ſhould be enemies, whereas true grace makes of the greateſt enemies ſtrongeſt friends? can it be? Poore men! what an amazing myſtery and wonder is here? can it not be? that two men, both having true grace, may yet be divided and at enmity? what do you think of <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas?</hi> do not you beleeve they had both true grace? doe you not read of the ſharpe contention between them, and that but upon a light occaſion. See <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 35. But how can it be? (ſay you.) I anſwer, do you not yet know, that every man that hath true grace in him, hath yet withall ſome corruption in every facultie as well as grace? do you beleeve this from <hi>Paul?</hi> or are you turn'd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thariſts? if you do beleeve it, as you muſt, (or elſe deny the Scripture) then 'tis eaſie to unfold this myſtery you ſpeak of, thus: Though true grace cannot be an enemy to grace, yet two men that have both true grace may for ſome time be at variance, and enemies to each other, through the corruption that is in them.—how do you think now? may not a man that hath true grace, be ſaid to embrace true grace, pietie, and holineſſe, though it come from the boſome of an enemie, and yet not be an enemie to grace? do you think that if men of underſtanding ſhould come to ſee your ſimplicitie, they would not hiſſe at it. For my part, I heartily pitie you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next place you ask me what I mean by true grace; And how ſhall you know it but by the ſignes thereof, in obedience to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will of God in his Word? And if ſo, you beſeech me to convince you, wherein thoſe amongſt you I point at do walk contrary in word or action, and you are perſwaded of them, that they will be thankfull to me, and bleſſe God: if not, I muſt needs be convinc'd that I walk con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my profeſſion, and ſo you cannot but expect acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:117654:40"/> and ſatisfaction from me, If there be any truth or ingenuity in me</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer: 'tis truth. True grace in the ſoul, is beſt ſeen and known by the effects thereof, ſeen in a mans obedience to the revealed will of God in his Word. The tree is known by its fruits, and a fountain by the water it ſends forth: ſo grace is beſt ſeen, to be in the heart (by us who can judge onely according to the outward appearance) by the fruits of it in a gracious life. Now would you be convinc'd wherein any amongſt you do walk contrary to the revealed wil of God in his Word? 'tis the eaſieſt thing of a thouſand to do that; and you cannot but be convinc'd of it, (if you be not like <hi>Solomons</hi> fool, which though he be brayd in a morter, yet he will retain his folly) I will inſtance in a few particulars. 'Tis the revealed will of God, that there be no diviſions among you: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. that you ſhould mark thoſe that cauſe diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and avoid them; as men that feed their own bellies, and ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 18. You walk contrary to this; for you do not avoid, but receive, uphold, follow, and countenance ſuch fellows, of whom 'twill be made good, that in what place ſoever they have come, they have made, and cauſed, ſuch unhappy breaches, and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as have been made, and are now amongſt you. Let the hand be layed upon the heart, and ſee if conſcience doth not bear witneſſe to you of this thing: have there not been formerly an happy union, a ſweet concord, a ſweet conſpiring together in the love of the ſame truth, in the communion of the ordinances of Chriſt, and in private duties? which truth and ordinances (though now condemned by you as abominable) yet I here again proffer to make good to you, to be no other then the truths and ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, (and your own conſciences will make good to you, that your own ſouls have received comfort by them) and you know that God hath enabled ſome of you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſuffer for them. Now as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 2, 3, 4. <hi>Who hath bewitcht you? have ye ſuffered ſo many things in vain? (if it be yet in vain.) Are there not now envyings, ſtrife, diviſions, and contentions amongſt you:</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. beg: Do you not now ſpeak evill of that way of truth you have formerly walked in, and found comfort in? is it not ſo? Now who hath cauſed this ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, envying, ſtrife, diviſion, contention, &amp;c. is he marked by you, and do you endeavour to avoid him? If you do not, you muſt needs be convinc'd in this, that you walk contrary to the revealed will of God. Again, I need go no farther then your Paper to convince you of your walking contrary to the revealed will of God in his Word: you have ſent it to me under your hands, and therefore I muſt look upon it as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:117654:40"/> your words, your act and deed. Let me inſtance in a particular or two.</p>
               <p>Is it not the revealed will of God that you ſhould know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and to admoniſh you, and to eſteeme them very highly in love for their works ſake, and to be at peace among your ſelves: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 12, 13. <hi>Is it not Gods will that they that labour among you ſhould be counted by you worthy of double honour,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 7, 8. Now let me aske you? hath not God in mercy, ſet thoſe over your ſelves that labour in word and doctrine? hath not God given a ſeale and a teſtimony to their miniſtry by begetting ſome of you againe by the word preached by them? and nouriſhing others amongſt you by the word of their miniſtry? and have they not been highly eſteemed amongſt you for their works ſake? have they not been ſought to by you to come among you again? have you not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them as a bleſſing? now let Conſcience anſwer. Doe you not now walke contrary to theſe commands of God in his Word? and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your former practice? Are they not looked upon as enemies becauſe they tell you the truth? inſtead of eſteeming them very high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love, are not both their perſons and doctrine, nay their very cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and miniſtery (which I ſay againe, I challenge you to prove, if you can to be any other then the Miniſtry of Jeſus Chriſt) are not theſe I ſay deſpiſed, ſcorned, reproacht by you? and branded even with the higheſt brand of being Antichiſtian. Let me aske you (my brethren) are not theſe things ſo? The Lord knowes (that's our comfort) and you ſhall know too one day, if you doe not now.—Now is not this a walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to the revealed will of God? are theſe the fruits of grace thinke you?—Againe 'tis the revealed will of God in his word, that putting away lying, every man ſhould ſpeak truth with his neighbour, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 25. Now I thinke I have made it appeare, (and ſhall make it appeare farther) that this Paper which you have ſet your hands to, hath not one page of it, but what is ſtuft with lyes and falſehood: I leave to the Lord, and to the world to judge (betwixt us) of them. And therefore here again you have walked contrary to the revealed will of God.</p>
               <p>Againe. 'Tis the revealed will of God that you ſhould not backbite with your tongue, nor doe evill to your neighbour, nor take up a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, againſt your neighbour, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 3. Againe that all bitterneſſe, anger, wrath, clamour and evill ſpeaking be put away, with all malice, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 31. Now looke upon your Paper. There you call us Praters, Time-ſervers, Weathercocks, blinde Phariſees, Miniſters of Antichriſt,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117654:41"/> Popiſh perſecutors of the Saints, haters of godlineſſe, lovers of propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, falſe Apoſtles, ſelfe ſeekers, penny Maſters, Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars, men that endeavour to keep others in ignorance, Seducers, men of no religion, proud, covetous, blood thirſty men, for-ſwearers, vain teachers, men of perfidious opinions, that we preach deſtructive and damnable doctrines, deſtroyers of truth, and true religion, perfidious men, that will deſtroy ſoules for gain, Ale-houſe hunters, Hereticks, Jews, Monſters, men that condemne the practice and precepts of Chriſt for hereſie, enemies to true grace, Miniſters of Antichriſt, nay Divels. This is the language you afford us in your Paper; and you have ſet your hands to it that we are ſuch as theſe. Now whether this be a walking according to the Word, or contrary to the revealed will of God in his word, let your own conſciences be Judges; or elſe let the Lord (the righteous Judge) judge betwixt you and us.</p>
               <p>I thinke I need goe no farther in this particular, I hope this may be ſufficient to convince you (if the Lord will ſet it on upon your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) and if ſo, then be thankfull and bleſſe God for it, if there be any truth or ingenuity in you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> In the next particular you tell me, you are grieved in ſpirit, to ſee and heare my light and frothy carriage, in the mentioning of Scripture, as to ſay that's a nimble Place. You ſay a carnall and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heart will abuſe the beſt thing, even grace, mercy, and love: you ſay a Stage Player could doe no more, nor the Divell himſelfe to abuſe and mock at Scripture, and you cloſe thus;—for ſhame come not in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to act ſuch Diabolicall parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer.—This whole accuſation is from the Divell the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lyes too: you are grieved (you ſay) to ſee and heare, pray how many of you ten, dare ſay you ſaw and heard me in that carriage or that expreſſion which you have here ſet your hands to? if I am not much miſtaken, not neare the one halfe of you, and yet you have ſet your hands to it, I hope you will not turn Knights of the poſt,—theſe be ſome ſteps towards it. Me thinks you ſhould not call men Divels, meerly upon heare ſay; if you had any Charitie in you, you could not; he or they, that informed the reſt of you of this, may be aſhamed to looke an honeſt man in the face; (as we ſay) to come to Publicke ordinances, under a pretence of worſhipping, and to bely the truth of God in this manner; the Lord will finde out ſuch one day.—But (as you ſay) a carnall and wicked heart will abuſe the beſt things: I am able to bring you twenty for one of your informers of this, who will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:117654:41"/> paſſe (I beleeve) both in the preſence of God and account of men, for as honeſt conſcientious Chriſtians as your informer, whoſoever he be of you, that will be witneſſes, that there was no ſuch word ſpoken, and I call God (that heard and recorded every word) to witneſſe of it.—You tell me that a Stage Player a Devill could have done no more.—</p>
               <p>I anſwer.—For what I did, and ſpeak then, and there in publicke, the Lord knows, that (as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Michal)</hi> it was before the Lord, and for the Lord; and if this be, to be vile, and a carnall wicked man, a Stage Player, a Divell, I ſhall deſire that I may be more vile yet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper,</hi> You bid me not come in publick for ſhame to act ſuch Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> When the Lord ſhall again call me, I ſhall not be aſhamed to come again in publick, and to act that part, which the Lord hath put me upon:—as for your expreſſion <hi>Diabolicall,—</hi>the Lord forgive you; I do; and I value it not. The Lord Jeſus hath taught me, that <hi>the diſciple is not above his Maſter, nor the ſervant above his Lord. If they have called the maſter of the houſe Beelzebub, how much more ſhall they call them of his houſhold? Fear them not therefore: for there is nothing covered, that ſhall not be revealed, and hid, that ſhall not be known.</hi> Matth. 10. 24, 25, 26.</p>
               <p>In the next place you come to make your requeſts to me—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paper.</hi> Firſt, that I would define what hereſie is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I define hereſie thus:—Hereſie is a voluntary chuſing of an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, againſt ſome Article of Faith without ground of Scripture, and an obſtinate maintaining of it againſt all lawfull determinations of the true Church, for ſome ſiniſter and particular reſpects.—Or if you will have it more briefly, thus:—Hereſie is an error in the foundation of Chriſtian Religion taught and defended with obſtinacy: Thus <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. 11. that an Heretick is perverted, that is, put beſides the foundation, and condemned of himſelf in his ſin, that is, he erres ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately.</p>
               <p>This hereſie is differenced from a ſimple error, by its obſtinate main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining; from a ſchiſme, for that ſchiſme is in diſcipline, hereſie in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, from Heatheniſh ſuperſtition, Jewiſh perverſneſſe, ſtup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metiſme, and the like, becauſe hereſie is a revolt from the faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God; which ſuch never had, no profeſt.—The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it is the devill; the mother, pride; the nurſe, ſingularitie; the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant, hypocriſie; the promoters of it, inticing perſwaſions, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory will-worſhip; Apoſtacie is an eminency in it, it being a falling away from the truth profeſt, ſelf-condemning the top of it. The out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:117654:42"/> of it, will be blaſphemy againſt God, virulent perſecution of his Church and children: The end finall impenitencie and deſpair; the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall fore-runners of eternall damnation.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſhewed you what Hereſie is; you may eaſily reſolve your ſelves the 2d. <hi>Quaere</hi> what an Heretick is. And can likewiſe beſt ſatisfie your ſelves in the 3d. <hi>viz:</hi> whether there be any ſuch among you. The Lord help you to ſearch narrowly, and to deal truly with your ſelves, that if there be any amongſt you, you may ſee them, and beware of them.</p>
               <p>For your 4th deſire, to ſatisfie you in that, I give you all this under my hand. And for the 5th. I leave it to the world to judge, whether I have anſwered it or no.</p>
               <p>And whereas in your cloſe, you again deſire a meeting in a ſober and in a Chriſtian way, I have told you my mind before, and here tell you again that the moſt ſafe and ſure way, to cleare up the truth, to ſatisfie doubts, to diſcover errors, to eſtabliſh Saints that are wavering, wil be to deal by ſetting down under yours and my hand, what we would ſpeak face to face at ſuch a meeting; one thing we ſhall more probably avoid this way, (which would fruſtrate our endeavours in the other) that is, clamour, paſſion, and tumults. Again from written words we ſhall not ſo ſoone ſtart and fly, as from words ſpoken (which in ſuch a way with ſuch people have ſeldome proved any better then wind.)</p>
               <p>For my part, I profeſſe it in the preſence of God, that it is, and by Gods grace ſhall be my endeavour, that love may be increaſed, that jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies, heart burning and evill ſurmiſings may be removed: And that we may live in love and peace as becomes Chriſtians. I truſt the Lord Jeſus who is the great Prophet of his Church, and the teacher of Iſrael, will alwayes direct me, not onely to ſpeak of, but to endeavour after the peace of the Church, by convincing and ſtopping the mouthes of gainſayers, who are crept in to diſturbe our Peace, by perverting the truths of God once delivered to the Saints. And my prayers in ſpeciall are, that that God, whom I ſerve in my ſpirit, who knoweth the heart and prayers of his ſervant, would onely ſo be with me in theſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of mine, as it is the truth which I endeavour to maintain.<hi>—Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſubſcribe your ſelves, My loving friends, ſo farre as I love the Lord Jeſus.—</p>
               <p>For your love and friendſhip to me, I know not how I have of late forfeited it. There are but few ſignes of it at preſent to be ſeen. But for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:117654:42"/> love to the Lord Jeſus, I here ſet my heart, tongue, pen, to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> as the concluſion of his Epiſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 22. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>March—</hi>1648. </date>
                     <hi>Kemble.</hi>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours to ſerve you in the work of the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> THO: THACHE.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
                  <p>FRiends; If hereupon you finde grace to ſee, and heal your Errors, we ſhall with all brotherly meekneſſe, love, and humilitie, be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to receive you, and ſhall bleſſe God on your behalf: But if the ſway of your miſ informed and miſ-reſolved Conſcience be heady and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable, and your return hopeleſſe;—Even theſe poore endeavours of mine, ſhall one day be a fearfull and materiall evidence againſt you, before that awfull Judge who hath already ſaid, <hi>That judgements are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſcorners, and ſtripes for the back of fools.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
